<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vertuous scholehous of vngracious women A godly dialogue or communication of two systers [...]</title>
            <title>Bösen Weiber Zuchtschül. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 98 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11581</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21826.6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851007</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851007</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16259</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11581)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16259)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 50:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vertuous scholehous of vngracious women A godly dialogue or communication of two systers [...]</title>
                  <title>Bösen Weiber Zuchtschül. English.</title>
                  <author>Lynne, Walter.</author>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546. Fruteful predication or sermon of D. Mart. Luth. concernynge matrimony.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[194] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[S. Mierdman for W. Lynne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1548?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts; register is continuous. Part 1 is a translation of Der bösen Weiber Zuchtschül. Part 2 is a translation of a sermon on matrimony by Martin Luther. Part 2 begins on H verso and has a caption title that reads: A fruteful predication or sermon of D. Mart. Luth. concernynge matrimony, vpon this texte, in the Epistle to the Hebrewes, in the xiii. chapiter .. .</note>
                  <note>Translated by Walter Lynne. Preface headed: "Gwalter Lyn to the reader".</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from and publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁶ E-G (-G8) [H]-M N⁴.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 12104.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 12104 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; copy is imperfect as filmed; print faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:1"/>
            <p>¶The vertu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous ſcholehous of vngraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous women. ☞A godly dialogue or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of two Syſters. The one a good and vertuous wedowe, oute of the land of Meiſſen. The other, a curſt vngracious, froward and brawlinge woman, oute of the mountaynes. To the honour and prayſe of all good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. And to the rebuke and inſtrucci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuche as be vnpacient.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of two women conversing by a tree</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:2"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prouerb xix. b.</bibl>☞Houſe and ryches may a man haue by the heritage of hys elders. But a diſcrete woman is the gyfte of the Lorde.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prouerb. xxxi b.</bibl>☞ Who ſo fyndeth an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt faythfull woman, ſhe is more worth then pearles. The harte of hys huſbande may ſafely truſt in her, ſo that he ſhall haue no nede of ſpoyles.</q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Gwalter Lyn to the reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Paule to the Romaynes in the xv. writeth that, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer is wrytten afore, is wrytten for oure le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arnynge and inſtruction. Wherfore in thys Dialogue chriſten reader, thou findeſt a very godly communicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betwene two Syſters.</p>
            <p>Iuſtina a Godly wydowe out of the lande of meyſſen. Serapia a waywarde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly maryed woman. This complayneth vpon her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande, and wilfull children. The other inſtructeth and conforteth her in pacience,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:3"/> to be obedient vnto her wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded huſband, and to brynge vp her children in the feare of God, with fayre wordes, &amp; decent nurtour and correcti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, groundyng theſame in the holy ſcripture of God, &amp; confirmynge theſame by ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny goodly examples, for Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina is alwayes mynded to lyue godly, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywyſe Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rapia, whiche bylyke recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that name at the fonte. And doutles, yf honeſt and vertuous huſwyues or wydo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes ſhall ſe, reade or heare thys dialogue, they ſhall ſtrengthen theyr vertuous myndes in it. Agayne, yf ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, in apte ſtubborne wyues ſhall alſo heare the ſame, thei ſhall take occaſion to knowe
<pb facs="tcp:16259:3"/> them ſelues and to amende their conditions. Wherfore Chriſten reader, voucheſafe to iudge, and vnderſtande the ſame with a godly myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and accepte it for good, for aſmuche as it is digeſted after the ſimpelwitted natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re and inordinate ſpeache of women. And here in is no ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le preſcrybed vnto the good, nor yet any correction layde to heauy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ignorant.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:4"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of two women conversing by a tree</figDesc>
                  <p>Iuſtina</p>
                  <p>Serapia</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vſtina.</speaker>
               <p>God ſpede my hartly beloued ſiſter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>oh it is good y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou doeſt ones come to me, but ye ſtately folkes in your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre care not for vs poor ſoules he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re without. In this countre God thanke the good Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:4"/> thou arte hartely wilco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vnto me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>My dearly beloued ſyſter. God thanke the, howe canſt thou ſaye, that I am to ſtately for the, I haue reioyced hartely to come vnto the, thynkeſt thou alſo, that I care not for the, notwithſtondynge that thou knoweſt well ynough, that I haue alwayes loued the before other of oure ſyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Therfore I come to the nowe, to viſyte the, and to ſe how thou doeſt, Simplicius thy good man, and thy louin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge children.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>O ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we do verely, I coulde be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to take it better, with vs is nothing but labor and trauayll, and yet haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:16259:5"/>
               <p>Oh deare ſyſter, complayne not to I praye the, thanke the heauenly father, that he geueth helth vnto thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge huſband and childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche is the greateſt gyfte and grace of God, and alſo the coſtlyes treaſure in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. Alſo let it not be tedious but pleaſyng vnto the, that God cauſeth not al thynges to ſuccede vnto the, after thy ne owne mynde and wyll as vnto the vngodly, where of Dauid ſayth. I was greued at the wicked, whan I ſawe the vngodly in ſuche proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte, for they are in no parel of death, but are luſty and ſtronge. They come in no miſfortune as other folke, neyther are they plaged ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
<pb facs="tcp:16259:5"/> other men. Lo (ſayth he) theſe are the vngodly, theſe proſpere in the worlde, and theſe haue ryches in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but be thou of good chere and thinke that thou arte in the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of the godly, and ſaye with Dauid,<note place="margin">Pſa. xij. Num. xiiij. ii. Eſa. l. b ro. viijd</note> whan I haue the Lorde. I care not for heauen nor earth, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>playne not, that it is labour &amp; trauayll, with our laboure and trauayll can we not ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue in this worlde.<note place="margin">Gene. iij. c</note> For the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de God hath layed thys cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and malediction vpon the ſhoulders of all men, in hys wrath, euen in Paradyſe, that we becauſe of oure tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, muſt eate our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ade in the ſweate of oure fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in laboure and ſorrowe.
<pb facs="tcp:16259:6"/> Thou nedeſt not to ſaye, alſo that thou haſt nothynge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes, thou wilt not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with that, whiche God hath geuen the, and yet ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth dayly, where by I may perceyue, that thou haſt but ſmal truſt in God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>yea, the longer I truſte, the leſſe I haue. The daye hath ben, that I had ſomewhat, but now all is gone to the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyll.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>God ſaue vs from the Deuyll, good ſyſter ſpeake not ſo waywardely, knoweſt thou not, that euen as God is beleued and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, euen ſo is he had &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de? yf thou beleue that he wil preſerue the, thy good man and thy children, truely he ſhall do it, and wyl do it with
<pb facs="tcp:16259:6"/> a good wyll, but yf thou do miſtruſt hym, and be doute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the mater, thinkynge that thou muſt proſecute &amp; brynge it to paſſe, by thy ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, labour, and paines,<note place="margin">Prou.</note> than ſendeth God ſcarcite. For whatſoeuer the vngodly fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth the ſame cometh vpon hym. Thys doth he for thys cauſe, that we ſhulde knowe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge that he is almightye, and that we of our owne po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, without hys grace ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do nothynge.<note place="margin">i. Pet. a Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> c Luc. xi Pſalm lv. c.</note> Therfore caſte all thy care (ſayth Peter, vpon the lorde, for he careth for vs, he wyl alſo (as Dauid ſayth) not alwayes leaue the righteous and them that truſt in hym, in tribulacion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt very
<pb facs="tcp:16259:7"/> well deare ſyſter. Thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſt truſt in God wel ynough for thou arte ryche, and haſt ynough. But yf the worlde were ſo hard with the, as it is with me, thou ſhouldeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>playne as well as I. For I ſe wel ynough, whan I ſitte longe ſtill, and care not, or do nothynge, than haue I nothynge, I muſt ſurely ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and do for it, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will bringe me ought at home, Al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo my huſbande is ſeldom at home, he goeth furth aboute hys buſynes, and careth not howe I kepe hous with the children.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Vvith all thy carefulnes and ſekynge, ſhalt thou preuayl nothing, deare ſyſter, remembre the kynde wordes of Chriſte, and
<pb facs="tcp:16259:7"/> print them ſurely in thy har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, whereas he ſaieth.<note place="margin">Matth. vi. Luc. xij.</note> Be not carefull for your lyfe, what ye ſhall eate, or what ye ſhall drynke, nor yet for your body, what ye ſhall put on, is not the life more worth then meat, and the body mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re of valewe then rayment? Beholde the foules of the ay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, for thei ſowe not, neyther reape, nor yet cary into the barues, and yet your heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father fedeth them. Are ye not moche better then they? Vvhy care ye then for rayment? Conſidre the lily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the felde, howe they growe. They labour not, nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſpinne. And yet for all that, I ſaye vnto you, that euen Salomon in all hys
<pb facs="tcp:16259:8"/> royaltye, was not arayed lyke vnto one of theſe. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take no thought ſayen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, what ſhall we eate, or what ſhal we drinke, or whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re with ſhall we be cloteth? After all theſe thinges ſeke the gentyles. Therfore be not lyke vnto the heathen, frettinge and vexinge thy ſelfe, with ſuche vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cares and thoughtes, for the wyſe Salomon ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, Carefull trauayll hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, but bleſſed is he that truſteth in the Lorde.<note place="margin">Mat. vi</note> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte ſayth further in the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter aboue mentioned. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ye firſte the kyngdome of heauen, &amp; the righteouſnes thereof, &amp; al theſe thinges ſhal be miniſtred vnto you,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:8"/> for your heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue nede of meat drynke cloth &amp; all theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. Thys conforte ſhouldeſt thou truely take to thy hart deare ſyſter, and truſt there to. I haue ſuche a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in my God, &amp; in theſe confortable wordes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, that althoughe I wyth my poore fatherles children, had nothinge at al, or as lyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tell as thou, howe be it thou haſt ynough, and nedeſt not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playne, yet do I knowe ſurely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll not forſake me, but nouryſſhe me &amp; my chyldren, as the byrdes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayer, &amp; cloth me as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> floures &amp; lilyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felde. That thou ſaieſt, thy huſbande goeth and executeth hys offyce, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnreaſonable Pius
<pb facs="tcp:16259:9"/> my deare huſbande (whome God pardon) dyd ſo likewiſe I thought, yf he had not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ben at home, nothyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge had gone froward. But nowe I knowe, that he dyd more wyth one worde, than I can do in a hole daye, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we begynne I fyrſt to myſſe hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>No I can not tell what good he doth, he is nowe ſo ſtubborne and waywarde towardes mee &amp; the children, that I knowe not, howe it cometh to paſſe, or what he ayleth, he fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and vexeth hymſelfe, in vayne and for nought. I thynke he wyl be ſtarke mad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de or oute of hys wittes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>O good ſyſter, I be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue that thou arte the grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt
<pb facs="tcp:16259:9"/> occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his fretting and diſquietynge, thou arte to frowarde and obſtinate, agaynſt hym (as I heare) thou doſt not ſuffer hym a worde, brawleſt alwai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es with hym, and ordereſt hym very euyll, notwitſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge he is an honeſt ſimple man, which is loth to fyghte and brawle with the, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther frowarde men do. And alſo I beleue, and am ſure, that he is no dronkarde, hoo remonger nor player.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Howe a dronkar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, hooremonger, or player? yf he were ſuche one, Oh, then woulde I haue a ſtoma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke with hym, I would pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke my ſelfe with hym, as the one deuyll with the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:16259:10"/>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Lo, nowe I percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue what is in the, and that thou arte ſo ſtoute and way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde agaynſt the good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He hath alſo deſyred me, to rebuke the gentely for it, Oh ſayd he, thou ſuffereſt no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reproue the, alſo thou wilt not heare hym, ſpeake he ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer ſo kyndely vnto the, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther arte thou willinge to go to the worde of God, or preachynge, and alſo thou loueſt not to heare hym rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de at home (whiche is a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of an vngodly conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on) chydeſt with hym, euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more before men, bringeſt not vp thy children in the fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>are and correction of God, angreſt thy ſelfe vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly
<pb facs="tcp:16259:10"/> by and withoute a cauſe, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſagreeſt with thy neyghbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. Shoulde not thys gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thy good huſbande? I be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue or a trueth that thou doeſt greue hym ſore with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Vvhat care I for that? Although I am fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, ſeynge many ſpiteful tonges do reporte it by me, ſo that I am no hoore as ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me be. Alſo I knowe very well, that my huſbande eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where maketh hys repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of me, what ſhulde I do to hym? ſhoulde I call hym gracious Lorde? I woulde rather ſe hym hanged. Wel wel, I wil one daye begynne a matter with hym, that he ſhall not thinke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>God forbidde, let not ſuche e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill
<pb facs="tcp:16259:11"/> thoughtes entre into thy herte, but I perceyue that (as Chriſte ſaith) of the aboundaunce of the herte the mouth ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Mat xij</note> nowe do thy frutes breake forth, nowe arte thou lyke vnto vnbluſſhed lymeſtone, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che whan colde water is pou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it bloweth breaketh ſmoketh and burneth vnna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turally, euen ſo doeſt thou al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo, I haue ſomwhat gentily admonyſſhed and frendly reproued the (howe be it I thought thou wouldeſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue taken it for none euill of me) but thou vſeſt vngraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wordes, curſeſt thy good huſbande, whome by reaſon thou oughteſt to kepe in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, be obedient vnto him,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:11"/> as vnto the lorde, and alſo be not thy huſbandes mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter (as Paule teacheth but be ſtyll, ſhoulde not ſuche vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gracious, yea I will ſaye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vngodly wordes greue thy good man, and prouoke hym to anger? Oh be aſhamed, I heare no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſpeaketh euill by thy huſbande, but that he is good and honeſte, gentyll, courteous, &amp; lyueth charitably with al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any contention or deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, glad to heare and to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the worde of God, and to further the ſame, and that the people are very fauoura<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble and louinge towardes hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>I knowe that well ynough, that the folles loue hym, and ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:16259:12"/> ſome wyues loue hym ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wel, thou nedeſt not to tel me thereof, but yf I may co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ones to the ryght groun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of the matter, thou ſhalt ſe, what I wyl do, alſo I paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe not for his goynge to chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, hearynge of ſermons, or readynge, the more he goeth to Churche or readeth, the leſſe I haue, &amp; ſence Luther, the newe preachinge, the he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reticall bokes and readyng came vp haue I almoſt loſte all that I had, and I thinke I ſhall neuer haue lucke with hym as longe as he ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, woulde god that the deuill woulde ſhortely ridde hym out of the waye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</speaker>
               <p>By thy frutes it is kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, what maner of tree
<pb facs="tcp:16259:12"/> thou arte, o, doeſt thou not truſte thy huſbande? &amp; ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt in feare of him, for other good women? god ſaue me, I take pitye vpon the, that thou arte ſuch a wilde and ſtubborne woman, what wilt thou ſhewe thy ſelfe? of a trueth I woulde not haue beleued it, if any man had tolde it me, but thou comeſt forth thy ſelfe with ſuche vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manerly communication be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore me, whereof by reaſon thou ſhouldeſt refrayne thy ſelfe, what doeſt thou then before other folkes? Oh nay deare ſyſter do not ſo, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt thou not that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is hys wyues heade,<note place="margin">Ephe. v i. Co. xi i. Pet. iij</note> and we wyues ought to be obedient and ſubiect vnto our huſban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:16259:13"/> in all thynges, euen as alſo God, hath geuen vnto the man in Paradiſe, the ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le ouer the woman, whereas he ſaieth.<note place="margin">Gen. iij</note> Thou ſhalt bowe before thy huſbande and he ſhall haue the rule of the. This is the cauſe alſo (as Paule ſayth) that we go at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyred and haue a power vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our heades,<note place="margin">i. Cor. ij</note> whereby we ſhoulde remembre, that we muſt lyue vnder the power and ſubiection of the man. And therfore muſt I nowe (for as much as my louynge huſband, of bleſſed memory, is dead) lette hange my po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer or vayle downewardes from my heade, whereby is ſignifyed that I am a wydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we, hauynge no power or
<pb facs="tcp:16259:13"/> huſbande that nowe hath rule of me. Thou ſayeſt alſo that thou doeſt not paſſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy huſbandes goynge to Churche, hearynge of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, or readynge, notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandynge that we haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge in earth more bleſſed more profitable, and better, then to heare and reade the worde of God,<note place="margin">Matth. iiij. Deute. viij</note> we are alſo nouryſſhed, and lyue by eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry word that procedeth oute of the mouth of god, and not onely by bread. Nowe yf thy huſbande alſo ſhoulde not heare or reade the worde of God, where by all thinges are ſanctified, and be ſo fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, wilde and vnmane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as thou, whiche feareſt not God, &amp; canſt agree with
<pb facs="tcp:16259:14"/> no body. Oh, what alyfe ſhoulde that be? And beleue me truely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou, thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and the hole hous, is ſanctified and preſerued of God through thy vertuous huſbande,<note place="margin">Co. vij</note> as Paule ſaieth, that the vnbeleuyng wyfe is ſanctifyed by the huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, or els ſhoulde all thinges go to wracke with the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pia.</speaker>
               <p>What ſhoulde he ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie me, if he myght drowne me in a ſpone full of water, he woulde do it, he kepeth me ſome tyme lyke a diſh clou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, thinkeſt thou, that I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it? No I warraunte the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtyna.</speaker>
               <p>Truely, thou haſte a ryght name Seropia or Serapia, ſeldom or very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell good, thou haſte eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb facs="tcp:16259:14"/> name with the deade. But this I knowe of a trueth, &amp; haue perceyued it, that thy huſbande, is but the gentyll to good, ſimple, &amp; kynd, and geueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> no ſtrypes, kepeth the reaſonably &amp; honeſtly (wherfor he may well be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Simplitiꝰ) &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth all thinges for the beſt, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlyeſt of all then doeſt thou ſoberate hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpiteful wordes, that it is ſhame, ſhoulde not this greue hym? ſhoulde not this frette &amp; vexe him?<note place="margin">Pro. xij.</note> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch a ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mefull, vngentill, vnmane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, waiward woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is a cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in her huſbandes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And in another place ſayth he. A froward woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:15"/> woundeth the harte, to wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the harte, truely greueth a man ſore ſayth Salomon and geueth counſayl, ſaien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge that it is better to dwell in a very bare lande, then with ſuch a chyding, Ireful and froward woman. In ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke maner he ſpeaketh alſo of the good women ſayenge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a reſonable meke and vertu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous woman,<note place="margin">Pro. xij.</note> is a crowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her huſbande. Suche a good and diſcrete woman ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth god, &amp; in another place ſayth he. A gentyll wyfe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth her huſband glad, and nouryſſheth hys bones, yea ſhe is hys wyſedome.<note place="margin">Proue. xviij.</note> And whoſoeuer (ſayth he) findeth ſuch a wyfe, findeth a good thynge, and receyueth a hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſome
<pb facs="tcp:16259:15"/> benefite of the lorde. Therfor deare ſyſter, let not ſuche vngodlines and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes be ſpoken of the, for it is a great ſynne before God, and before the worlde great ſhame, take the good women of the olde Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for an example, be pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as Lea, frendly as Ruth, true vnto thy huſband, as Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chell, the wyfe of Dauid, me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſurable as Iudith, meke as Heſter, chaſte as good Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna, and obedient vnto thy huſbande, as Rebecca, Remembre that thy huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de is thy lorde,<note place="margin">i. Co. xi Ephe. v</note> and thy head euen as Chriſte is the Lorde and heade of the congregati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">i. Co. vij</note> and that thou haſt no po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer ouer thy body, but thy
<pb facs="tcp:16259:16"/> huſbande, and put thy truſt in God. And be of a lowly ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite, that thou mayeſt be cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led a doughter of Sara.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rapia.</speaker>
               <p>yf I knowe the not, I ſhoulde thinke, that thou were a waylyſſhe woman, becauſe that thou canſt tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ſo well, thou ſhouldeſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue well for a preacher, thou arte well ſene in ſcripture, and depely learned, what hath my huſbande geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the, that thou thus doeſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me, thou doeſt it not of thy ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Thou cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt it Chapterynge but kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weſt thou what Chapteryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge is? In tymes paſt was it, and is yet the vſe amonge the freares, that euery fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daye before dyner, they ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
<pb facs="tcp:16259:16"/> them ſelues togeher in the chapiter houſe, where as euery one ſeuerally was conſtrayned to ſhryue hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and confeſſe hys fautes openly, whiche he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted thoroughoute the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly weke. After that dyd the Abbot or Priour geue a good diſcipline or correction, with roddes vnto ſuche as had de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued it, for their faultes, And if the Abbot or prioure had perpetrated ought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they were fayne to ſuffer it in lyke maner &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The holy ſaynt Paul, wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnto the Romaynes, Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Galathians, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp;c. certayn Epiſtles, whiche are diuided into Cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piters, wherein he teacheth
<pb facs="tcp:16259:17"/> the faythe in Chriſte, and the loue towardes our neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bours, after that he admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſheth them of the doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, whiche they had hearde of hym, at the laſt doth he al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo reproue them for certayne errours that were amonge them, euen as I do nowe to the, but I truſt that my cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter ſhall not be kept in vay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne vpon the, but that thou ſhalt there by be amended, and waxe good and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. I haue alſo receyued no gyftes of thy huſbande, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I thus rebuke the, but I am bounde in conſcience, &amp; of charitable loue, vnto the and to all men, in thys caſe or in other lyke caſes, yf I ſe any man erre, that I ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:16259:17"/> rebuke, and chapter hym for it charitably, yf any heare me and amende for it, than haue I wonne hys ſoule, In lyke maner arte thou and al men bounde to do the ſame alſo, and yf thou knowe any lack faute or errour in me (where of I am not fre) thou muſt alſo chapter me for it. I wyll followe the, and take it well in worth and amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de my faulte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou alwayes talke ſo gently with thy huſbande? diddeſt thou neuer anger hym? nor curſe hym? I kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we that thou haſte an haſty anger raigninge in the. I am ſurely, thou diddeſt not alwaies bake pancackes for hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Herken my
<pb facs="tcp:16259:18"/> dearly beloued ſyſter, I wyll tel the, howe I led my lyfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pius, my good man, (who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me God pardon) and howe he be ſtowed his lyfe with me Vvha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the almighty God, af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter hys godly ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces had coupled vs bothe together in mariage, I htought lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe. Nowe muſt we labour, care, ſcrape, and ſcratche, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may gette our lyuinge in this ſpitefull miſerable worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, I fared with my good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and familie very hardely in meate and drynke. I comme ſeldome to any preaching, to heare the worde of God. I woulde lende nothing to no man, and thought alwayes, that I muſt bryng it to paſſe by my carefulnes, laboure &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:16259:18"/> trauayll to waxe ryche, I thought not that God dyd care for me, or made me ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. Alſo I knowe not the godly ſayenge of Salomon, where he ſayth. It is very eaſy, and a lyght thyng vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde, to make a pore man ryche, neyther had I at that tyme ſo muche know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge, and truſt in God (whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che I wil ſpeake thanked be god, withoute any boaſte) as I haue nowe, but whan Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us my louinge huſbande ſawe, that I was ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and ſparyng, &amp; though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te by myne owne prouiſion, withoute the helpe of god, to be made ryche, he ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnto me gently with kynde wordes. My louyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge
<pb facs="tcp:16259:19"/> Iuſtina, I ſe a great lacke and faute in the, It pleaſeth my not that thou loueſt not to go to the ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to heare the worde of God, haſt no truſt in God, arte vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>willinge to lende to any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, kepeſt the houſe and familie to harde, and wilde be ryche al to haſtely, it will not fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſo, Paul ſaith to hys diſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple Thimothee.<note place="margin">i. tim. vi</note> They that wyll be ryche, fall into temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacions and ſnares, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many fooliſhe and noyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me luſtes, which drowne me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, into perdition, and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for couetouſnes is the rote of all euyll. Thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not be able to ſtande be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, nor yet before man. But thus muſt thou do. Firſt
<pb facs="tcp:16259:19"/> I will haue of the, that thou ſhalt loſe neuer a ſermon, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou be deſirous to heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt heard it, that thou pray vnto God for grace, that he will voucheſafe, to geue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fayth, and the frutes therof, that thou maieſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende thy lyfe, forgeue thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne aduerſary, be willinge to lende vnto thy neighbour. Although y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou thinkeſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhalte haue nothynge for it. God is able to ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de agayn, be in charite with all men, ſtryue with no man be not lichtely prouoked to anger (euen as we wyues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſone diſpleaſed) and kepe not thyne owne hous, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and familye, to ſtreigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:20"/> than ſhalt thou ſe and fyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, that god wyll dayly bleſſe the, and make thy partaker of hys bleſſynges and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, as the wyſe Salomon ſayth. The bleſſynge of the Lord, maketh ryche withou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te trauayll, the ſame bleſſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſhall be confortable &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable vnto vs in ſoule, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, honour, and goodes. &amp;c. By ſuche frendely wordes was I moued, that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde I folowed hym gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vntyll hys departynge, af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter that I went gladly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachyng, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had hear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god, I be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſought god (as Dauid) &amp; ſayd,<note place="margin">Pſal. li.</note> O my god make me a cleane hert, and renewe a ryght ſpirite within me. Caſte my not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye
<pb facs="tcp:16259:20"/> from thy preſence, and take not thy holy ſpirite fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me. Then did god heare me, and made me another woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> than I was afore, we lyued merely together god gaue vs goodly children, and goodes ynough for them, in ſomoche alſo that I knowe not fro whence it came. Then dyd I perceyue and ſe, that all oure care, labour &amp; trauayll (without the bleſſing of god) is loſt and in vayne, wherby we thinke to waxe ryche, whereas god geueth not, there hath no man ought, as Dauid ſayth,<note place="margin">Pſalm. cxxvij</note> It is but loſt laboure, that ye haſte to ryſe vp early, and ſo late ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke reſt, &amp; eate the breade of
<pb facs="tcp:16259:21"/> carefulneſſe. For vnto hys frendes, and vnto theſe that he fauoureth, and alſo vnto ſuche as truſte in hym, doth he geue it ſlepinge. Wherfor gentell ſyſter folowe not thy ne owne mynd and brayne, but folowe thy huſband, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as I knowe that he is ready alwayes to inſtructe the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, with the worde of God, &amp; other charitable wordes. Fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>are God. Be willinge &amp; glad to go to the ſermons, and to heare the worde of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche God for grace, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as I haue done, be not waiwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and angry at home with thy huſbande, children and familie. Be long ſufferinge, patient, and ſtryue not with thy neyghbours, and do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:16259:21"/> euery man, as thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be done to, than ſhalt thou ſe playnely before thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne eyes, and fynde, that God almightye ſhall ſende &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re hys bleſſynge vpon the, &amp; vpon thy hole houſe, &amp; ſhall geue the more, then thou ſhalt nede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>yea thou ſpeakeſt well, yf I had alwaies leaſure to go to chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, aſwell as thou and my huſbande, but I haue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elles to do, I can not ones go to churche, but the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is ſome hurte or myſchiefe done at home, or els I loſe ſomewhat, or ſomwhat eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth me, whiche might fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de me the hole weke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</speaker>
               <p>Haſte thou not hearde a prouerbe, whiche ſoundeth
<pb facs="tcp:16259:22"/> thus. The hearynge of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon loſeth nothynge, geuin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of Almes impoueriſſheth nothynge, and euill gotten goodes enrycheth nothyng. And thys prouerbe is true, as other godly ſcriptures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Thou ſayeſt, that thou lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſt moche, and that thou en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dureſt hurte and damage by thy goyng to churche, that is euen as moche to ſaye, as what haue I to do with god, hys worde or preachynge, I muſt do my buſynes, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge thy doynge, and care<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fulnes before the worde of god, as though thy cauſe we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re more neceſſary. Oh naye deare ſyſter, thou haſt heard that nothing is loſt, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge of a ſermon. And bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
<pb facs="tcp:16259:22"/> me truely, yf thou were deſyrous and willynge to go to the ſermon, and diddeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mende al thy mater at home to God, it ſhoulde go better with a great deale, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſhoulde be done, then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou doeſt ſcratche and rake ſo long at home. For we muſt firſt ſeke then kyngdome of God, and as then ſhall all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bodely neceſſaryes be miniſtred vnto vs, but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is aſhamed thereof (ſayth Chriſte) &amp; heareth not me wordes, of hym wil I alſo be aſhamed before my heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly father. Nowe haue we no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge vpon yearth to do more neceſſarye, neyther is there any thynge com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vnto vs more
<pb facs="tcp:16259:23"/> highly. Alſo we ought to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte none occaſion to hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or let vs from the hearin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of the worde of God, for therein are we taught, the fayth in God, and in Ieſus Chriſte hys ſonne, and the lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue towardes our neighbour but howe can we beleue, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Paule, yf we heare not the worde of God? how canſt thou beleue, &amp; put thy truſte in god? loue thy neyghbour, forgeue thyne enemyes, or howe wilt thou be ſaued, yf thou heare not the worde of god? but yf thou wilt obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne al theſe thinges, then go willingly to the ſermon, and heare the worde of god atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyuely with diligence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pia.</speaker>
               <p>Although men go to the
<pb facs="tcp:16259:23"/> church moche and heare ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons dayly, yet do I ſe none that amendeth there by, the one can not aforde to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the ſunne ſhyneth vpon hym, &amp; the worlde wax<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth worſe and worſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</speaker>
               <p>Meruayll not at it that the world waxeth euil, thou mayſt not put the faute in the preachyng, or in the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of god, but in the hearers of it, which beleue it not, nor amende the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues for it. But let the worde of god be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, whan and where occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhall ſerue, for it goeth not forth ydel, it findeth ſome men, that beleue it, and are amended through it, as the Lorde god ſayth hymſelfe,<note place="margin">Eſa. lv.</note> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke as the rayne and ſnowe
<pb facs="tcp:16259:24"/> cometh downe from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; retourneth not thyther a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but wathereth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth maketh it fruteful &amp; grene, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may geue corne vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, &amp; bread to him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eateth. So the worde alſo, that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth oute of my mouth, ſhal not tourne agayn voyde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, but ſhall accomplyſhe me wil, and proſpere in the thinge, where vnto I ſende it. Wherfor let it not moue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole world be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at it, heare thou the word of god gladly &amp; earneſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. Pray vnto god for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith, lyue &amp; do thereafter, &amp; forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thy neighboure, ſo ſhalt thou proſper alſo, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde ſaith, &amp; al thinges ſhal ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de with the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>I
<pb facs="tcp:16259:24"/> coulde be content to ſe an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement. But to be at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne with them, and to ſpeake louingely vnto thoſe, that put me to hinderaunce, and help to begyle me. I wil not, I would rather ſe them at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuill, I will nor can not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it, vntil I be auenged on ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>There do I perceyue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as yet thou arte no Chriſtian, for thou wilt not, neyther canſt thou ſpeake kyndly vnto thy neyghbour, nor be at one with hym.</p>
               <p>Secondly, thou doeſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe thyne aduerſitye and miſfortune vnto men, and not vnto God, as though it were not the good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious pleaſure of God,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:25"/> that all thynges ſuccede not alwayes after thyne owne braynes, Thirdly, thou wilt not forget, nor forgeue thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne aduerſary, but deſyreſt to be reuenged vpon hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>I praye the heare me. I am at one with many folkes, that do good vnto me &amp; I agayn vn to them, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> myne aduerſitye ſhould co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me from god, that can not I beleue, in no wyſe I ſhoulde be in reſt longe ynough for oure lorde god, yf wicked peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple woulde let me alone. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a wyſe woman hath tolde me my fortune, that many wicked people ſhall trouble me, and that I ſhal haue no good fortune as long as me huſband lyueth, yet I muſt
<pb facs="tcp:16259:25"/> be at one with certeyne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for my huſbandes ſake, vntyll a tyme conuenient, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I maye be euen with them, for the ſhrewed tournes, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che they haue done me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina.</speaker>
               <p>The good lorde ſaue me, doeſt thou alſo beleue ſouthſayers, and olde miſcre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aunte witches?<note place="margin">i. Re. xxviij. d</note> Truely it is highly prohibited of God in the ſcripture. In ſo moche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kynge Saull ſped very euil, for as moche as he forſoke god, and aſked counſayl of a witche, whiche had a ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayenge ſpirite. In lyke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was alſo ſerued kynge Ahaſia, whiche ſoughte coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeill at hys Idoll Beelzebub wherfore beware, that thou geue no crede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to any ſoth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:26"/> or ſorcerers. Nowe herken vnto me, I can not forbeare but that I muſt an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere to theſe thre poyntes. Fyrſt thou ſayeſt, that thou arte at one and at peace w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, that do good vnto the &amp; that thou doeſt alſo good vnto them, what maner of vnity is that? where by a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may perceyue, that yf any of them, with whome thou arte nowe at peace, ſhoulde diſpleaſe the, thyne vnity &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>corde ſhould loue be at an ende with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">mat. viij Luc. vi.</note> And it is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as Chriſte ſayth, yf ye loue them, whiche loue you, what rewarde ſhall ye haue? for the Publicanes and very ſynners loue theyr louers. And yf ye do for them which
<pb facs="tcp:16259:26"/> do for you, what thanke are ye worthy of? for the very ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners do euen the ſame. But I ſaye vnto you (ſayth Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte) loue your enemyes. Do good to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which hate you. Bleſſe them that curſe you. Praye for them whiche wron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gefully trouble you. Bleſſe and curſe not ſayth Paull. Nowe concludeth Chriſte ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge, vnto him that ſmiteth the on the one cheke, offer al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo the other. And hym that taketh thy goune, forbidde not to take thy coate alſo. Geue to euery man that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the. And of hym that taketh awaye thy goodes, aſke them not agayne. He will not haue that we ſhall onely agree with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which
<pb facs="tcp:16259:27"/> do good vnto vs, but alſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, that Imagine all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchief agaynſt vs, and hurte vs, and that vnto them we ſhoulde do all good. Secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darely, thou beleueſt not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyne aduerſitie and miſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune cometh from god, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che cauſeth al good thynges and euil thinges, as the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de god ſayth hymſelfe, I am the lorde, and none other, whiche make the light, and cauſe the darkenes, which geue peace and cauſe the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll, I am the lorde whiche doth all theſe thinges. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge god doth al theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, howe dareſt thou then put the faulte vnto the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked people, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge, withoute the will
<pb facs="tcp:16259:27"/> of God are able to do nothin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, god doth alſo conforte vs whereas he ſaith, I am your conforter, who arte thou the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that arte afrayed of men? which notwithſtondyng are mortall, and of the children of men, whiche are deliuered vp as heye, &amp; forgetteſt the lorde, whiche created the, whiche ſpred oute the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and grounded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth. Euen as alſo no man was able to hurte or endamage the good Iob, vntyl god ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue power vnto Satan to proue hym. Chriſte ſayth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,<note place="margin">Mat. x.</note> that we ſhoulde not feare them, whiche hurte or kyll the body, for al the heares of our heades are nombred and none of them falleth on
<pb facs="tcp:16259:28"/> the grounde without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll of the heauenly father. He careth for vs, and loueth vs ſo moche, that he ſaith, He that toucheth vs, toucheth the appel of hys eyes. for whatſoeuer happeneth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, be it good or bad, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth al by thy good &amp; graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous will of God. But who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſayth Paule) reſiſte his will Therfore hath Chriſt taught vs to praye vnto the heauen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly father.<note place="margin">Mat. vi</note> Thy wyll be done in earth as it is in heauen. Therfore nedeſt thou not to aſſcribe vnto any man the good or euill whiche happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto vs, but onely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, whiche becauſe of oure ſynnes ſendeth vs ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitye. Thyrdely, thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="4 pages">
                     <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16259:28"/> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe was throwen down fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a wyndowe &amp; eaten of dogs. Me thinketh alſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to fearce &amp; deſyrous of ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geaunce againſt euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſpecially agaynſt thyne own children, for when any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth any thynge, which ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſeth the not, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doeſt thou auenge by and by, &amp; beateſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſore &amp; out of due tyme, wherof the children become dulwitted &amp; fearful.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia.</speaker>
               <p>I haue ſuche frowarde childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there are no worſe in al this land, yea I thinke verely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yonge Deuyls, for none of them wyll take any nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor correction at my ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, neyther doth any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regarde me, I can not tell
<pb facs="tcp:16259:29"/> howe to do with them, yf it were not for my huſbande, whome they dreade ſore. For yf I ſhoulde brynge them vp alone, truely I woulde bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te them all awaye from me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>That thyne, myne and other mennes children, are wilfull, and ſtubborne, is not to be meruayled at. For it is geuen vnto all men euen by nature from Adam, that all the myndes though<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and Imaginations of theyr hartes are euyll, and more inclined and prone to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is euyll then to that which is good. Therfor hath God ordeyned and geuen to the children parentes, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and mothers, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to all men Superiors, for
<pb facs="tcp:16259:29"/> to breake our wilfulnes, and oure owne myndes, and to drawe vs to the feare, &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and to all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and that we ſhoulde ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vnder theyr obedience. Therfor deare ſyſter inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te fyrſt thy children truely in the commandementes of God. accordynge as thou ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te bounde vnto them, and be gentyl to them. for wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are kept ſo harde &amp; ſtreighte and are brought vp in ſuche great feare, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> become they fearfull, wilde and ſtubborne people, when they growe to age whiche neyther care for father, nor yet for mother, and yf they growe vp ſo, thei are alſo diſobedient to all hy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er powers. Paule teacheth
<pb facs="tcp:16259:30"/> alſo, that we ſhould not brin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge them vp,<note place="margin">Eph. vi Coll. iij.</note> ſo ſtraighly, and be not ſo harde vnto them, moue them not to wrath, &amp; rate them not leaſt thei be of a deſperate mynd, but bring them vp with the nourture and information of the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Thou mayſt not alſo be to ſofte for them, nor ſuffer them to haue the brydell to large, that they waxe not wylfull, and deſpyſe the and thy huſbande, as it was ſene by Abſolon, and more other wicked children. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore hath Salomon taught often, that we ſhoulde kepe oure children vnder corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, not ſparynge the rod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de where as nede requireth, ſaynge.<note place="margin">Pro. xiij</note> He that ſpareth the
<pb facs="tcp:16259:30"/> rodde, hateth hys ſonne, but who ſo loueth hym, chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth hym betymes. And in an other place ſayth he,<note place="margin">Ecl. viij and xxx</note> yf thou haue ſonnes, bryng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp in nourtoure and learnin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and hold them in awe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr youth vp. Moreouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture doth ſet before vs for an Example and a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which happened vnto the prieſte Ely and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his children,<note place="margin">i. Re. iij</note> becauſe that they were obſtacle agaynſte their father, and he was to ſlacke in correctynge of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. for it was their death, and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruction. Alſo thy correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be meaſurable, &amp; not to harde nor tyrannous, but fatherlyke &amp; motherlyke as Sal. ſaith.<note place="margin">Pro. xix</note> Chaſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſonne
<pb facs="tcp:16259:31"/> whyle there is hope, but let not thy ſoule be moued to ſlay hym. for great wrath bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth hurte, therfore delyuer hym, then mayeſt thou cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte hym more. Of ſuch har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and vnmeaſurable correc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, do we reade an Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple in Titus Liuius, of a certay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne Senatour of Rome cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Lucius Manlius, which dyd ſet furth a commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that noman ſhoulde preſume to fyght with the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes without a furder co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement, which hys ow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ſonne tranſgreſſed, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came and diſconfited the ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myes. Wherfore hys father cauſed hys head to be ſtrike<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of openly, not regardynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he therby had done good
<pb facs="tcp:16259:31"/> ſeruice to hys natiue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, and obtayned victory, honour and peace for it. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge as we reade, that Saul was alſo very harde vnto hys ſonne Ionathas, for an vnreaſonable cauſe etc. Thou ſhouldeſt alſo ſette them to ſcole or els kepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at theyr worke, and let them not go ydell, whereby they may be occupied and taught to forgette Idelnes in theyr youth, for whan a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goeth Idel, then doth he learne al euyll, as lyenge, deceyuyng, drinkyng, playenge, dicyng, louyng, and ſuch lyke. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſhouldeſt thou alwayes be doyng with them, and let<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te them thereof, and ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thy doughters, that they
<pb facs="tcp:16259:32"/> do not chaunce ſome where amonge euill company, and come to a ſhamefull fall, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it happened vnto Dina,<note place="margin">Eccl. vij</note> the doughter of Iacob. And the wyſe Salomon ſayeth and teacheth,<note place="margin">Geneſi. xxxiiij.</note> yf thou haue doughters, kepe theyr body and ſhewe not thy face chere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full towarde them. But whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re as thou ſayeſt that thou arte not able to rule thy chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, and to bryng them vp without thy huſbande, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſtrikeſt thou thy ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyne owne ſwearde, thou ſaydeſt afore, that thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt nothyng to do with thy huſband, &amp; dyddeſt not care (as I vnderſtode it) though he were dead, for the whiche I pray God, preſerue hym
<pb facs="tcp:16259:32"/> longe. O good ſyſter, what a poore lyfe ſhouldeſt thou lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de with thy ſmall children, thou knoweſt not yet, that a good man (eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thou haſt) is ſuche a coſtly Iewell in a houſſe, neither beleueſt thou that a wydowe with many childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though ſhe be neuer ſo ryche is ſuch a poore deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Truely thyne vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>profitable &amp; vncomly wordes wyl moue me to be angry, &amp; to fal out with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sera.</speaker>
               <p>Oh good Iuſtina be not angry, I will now waxe good, &amp; ſet vp another heade, though I ſhould fetche it out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of dead me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes bones, yf I knewe in dede, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhoulde chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of a better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſt.</speaker>
               <p>Alas what ſhould I do, how moch inſtruccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:33"/> admonicion, and gentyl cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, I ſpend on the, al is in vayne. For thou makeſt eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a geſt of it. Thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt not (ſayth Paul) let any filthy communication come out of thy mouth, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is good to edifye with al,<note place="margin">Eph. iiij</note> when nede is, that it may ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue faueour with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearers for of ſuch, and of euery ydel or vnprofitable worde,<note place="margin">Mat xij</note> muſte we geue accomptes before God, at the daye of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Therfore I beſeeche the gentyll ſyſter. It is true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more then tyme, for a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ful of filthy and vnpro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable communication, and withoute diſcrete maners (ſayth Salomon) is lyke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſowe,<note place="margin">Prou. xi</note> with a ryng of gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:16259:33"/> her noſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Doeſt thou nowe firſt lyken me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſowe, thou haſt comptrol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led me ynough, ceaſſe nowe, and let vs talke of an other matter. for I ſe wel ynough, that thou haſte no luſte to tary long with me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Who thinkeſt thou woulde be glad to be with the, ſeyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge thou chideſt and brawleſt ſtill, and noman can gette a good worde of the firſt I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue thy good huſband, that thou takeſt neuer a word for good, neyther of him, nor yet of noman elles, ſhoulde not thys greue hym? Verely I haue ſene in oure quarters, that ſuch an vndiſcrete and froward woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hath brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght her huſbande, to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlye.
<pb facs="tcp:16259:34"/> Wherfore refrayne thy ſelfe from ſo doyng, that there happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not a worſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge vnto the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Well let the matter reſt here, I be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeeche the, forgeue me good ſyſter Iuſtina, I wil do it no more from henceforth I knowledge that I haue ben very frowarde and euyl, but I wyl nowe take vpon me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother lyfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>For as muche as thou doeſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thyne offence, and wilt amend thy conditions, be it forgeuen vnto the.<note place="margin">Luc xvij</note> for Chriſt ſayth, yf thy brother or ſyſter offende, rebuke hym, and yf he repente and amende, for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geue hym &amp;c. Therfore do it no more, do not anger thy huſbande, neyther chyde,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:34"/> nor brawle with hym nor yet with other men. for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer enuyenge and ſtryfe is (ſayth Saynt Iames) the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re is vnſtablenes and al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of euyll workes.<note place="margin">Iaco. iij.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Iaco. iiij</note> Speake not euyl behynde other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes backes.<note place="margin">Luce. vi</note> Pull not a mote out of any mannes eye, as longe as thou haſte a beame in thyne eyes, that thou be not lyke vnto the man with the two powches, whereof the Hiſtories do wryte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pia.</speaker>
               <p>Vvhat maner of man was that? or what had he in hys two powches? I neuer hearde of him before in al my lyfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> will I tel y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, &amp; it is good to perceyue. Thus wryteth Eſopꝰ, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there was ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tym a ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cial ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which dyd
<pb facs="tcp:16259:35"/> backbite the people very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and prayſed himſelfe, ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinge alwaies two powches gyrded about hym, the one great, before hym vpon hys belly, which he myght ſe, the other littel, behynde hym v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon hys backe, whiche he coulde not ſe, Nowe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer fautes or euill he eſpied of hys neyghboures dyd he wryte vp, and layd them in the formoſt powche vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys belly, in ſo muche that the great powch waxed hole ful. But whatſoeuer he did back byte and ſlaunder hym ſelfe of other, the ſame coulde he, neyther write vp nor yet per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue, and the ſame layde he in the hyndermoſt powche vpon hys backe. Now whan
<pb facs="tcp:16259:35"/> and whereſoeuer he came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge companye, he put al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hys hande in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooſt powche, wherein he founde alwayes, all other mens fautes, wherfore he ſpake alwayes euill of other men. But he coulde not put hys hand into hys ſmal pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che vpon his backe, neyther had he put any thyng of him ſelfe in it, that is,<note place="margin">Luc. vi</note> he eſpyed alwayes a chippe or mote in his neyghbours eye, but the great beame in hys own eye he coulde not perceyue. And he was euen a fellowe lyke vnto the Phariſee in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, whiche boaſted &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hymſelfe of hys ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, and deſpiſed the poo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re publicane. Now mayeſt
<pb facs="tcp:16259:36"/> thou eaſely vnderſtonde the man with the two powches. Thou ſhalt fynde them to ſel painted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> papers, bye one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; let thy huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de rede it vnto the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>well I wil marke it diligently, I ſe well ynough that thou wilt tary no longer by my wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I deſyre the good ſyſter Iuſtina, for as moche as the new yere approcheth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou wilt leaue me ſomewhat for a newe yeres gifte or a toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherby I may remember y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, as my dearly beloued ſyſter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Vvhat ſhoulde I le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aue the?<note place="margin">Actu. iij</note> I haue nothynge, ſyluer and golde haue I not but ſuthe as I haue, I geue the (ſayth ſaynte Peter) and of that wyll I alſo make the
<pb facs="tcp:16259:36"/> partaker.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Vvhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou doeſt geue or participate vnto me theſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me wyll I thankefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, ſhute it vp in my herte and kepe it whyleſt I lyue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>wel, then wyl I lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue thy ſome thynge for a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we yeres gyft, and for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce, whiche ſhall be better (as Dauid ſayth) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many thouſande peeces of golde, I geue and leaue the Ieſus Chriſte, the ſonne of God, hys holy worde, and Goſpell, and the hoolſome doctryne of Paule.</p>
               <p>I beſeeche the, put awaye from the thy former naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty lyfe, and conuerſation, by whoſe luſtes &amp; errours thou arte corrupted, and renewe
<pb facs="tcp:16259:37"/> thy ſelfe in the ſpirite of thy conſcience and mynde, &amp; put on Chriſte the newe man, whiche is ſhapen after God, in true righteouſnes and ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynes, put away from the al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyenge, and for aſmuche as we are membres) ſpeake trueth with thy neyghbour Be not angry with thy huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande, nor yet with other fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, and let not the ſonne go downe ouer thy wrath, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue no place vnto the backbe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter or deuill, pleate the cauſe of the poore and nedefull,<note place="margin">Eph iiij</note> let no filthy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede forth of thy mouth, gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not the holy Ghoſt, let all bitternes, fearſnes, wrath, rorynge, and curſed ſpeakin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge be put awaye from the,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:37"/> with all maliciouſnes, be courteous and harty to all men and forgeue thyne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary, euen as God forga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the and vs al, for Chriſtes ſake. Remember alſo, that thou without any delaye, be willynge and glad to go to the ſermons, and deſyrous to heare the worde of God, And pray vnto God for gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, that it wil pleaſe hym to ſtrengthen the ſame in the, and to increace thy faythe. Alſo be not onely a hearer of the worde,<note place="margin">Iacob. i.</note> as Saint Iames ſaith, but declare it alſo with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dede vnto thy neyghbour, that thou deceaue not thy ſelfe, for Chriſt ſpeketh hym ſelfe. Bleſſed are they that heare the worde of God, and
<pb facs="tcp:16259:38"/> kepe the ſame, that is, that they lyue and do there after, accordynge as the holy ſaint Paule writeth vnto his ſcol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Titus,<note place="margin">Tit. ij.</note> and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth hym howe he ſhoulde teache and ſpeake vnto women, &amp; ſo wyll I alſo, ryght well be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loued ſyſter, deſyre and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the, and leaue the for a re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membraunce, that thou wal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke and behaue thy ſelues as becommeth holynes, that thou be no falſe accuſer, not geuen to moche drynkin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, but a teacher of good and honeſt thynges, to make the yonge women ſobreminded to loue theyr huſbandes, to loue theyr children, to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete, chaſte, huſwyfly, good &amp; obedient vnto their owne
<pb facs="tcp:16259:38"/> huſbandes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the worde of God be not euil ſpoken of, &amp; for to do all theſe thinges, de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyre God mooſt hertily of his grace, &amp; beleue without wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerynge, that he will geue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace to perfourme the ſame &amp; as Chriſt ſayth, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ye deſyre of the father in my name. I wyl do it. And whatſoeuer ye deſyre (vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that which perteyneth to ſaluacion and Chriſten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) beleue, and ye ſhall receyue it. Theſe and no bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter thynges haue I to leaue the forthy newe yeres gyfte or for a remembraunce, deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng that thou wilt alſo laye it vp, and kepe it diligently in the coffer of thy herte,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:39"/> then wyl God come, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the a newe herte &amp; a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we ſpirit (as the Prophet fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) then ſhalt thou ſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. li</note> that God with al hys graces and bleſſynges, wyll come vpon thy, vpon thy huſbande, thy children, and all thy houſſe, and that all thynges ſhal proſpere with the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke the gentyll ſyſter, that thou haſt ſo frendly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked, taught, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted me, I wyll neuer forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te it whyle I lyue, and I wil diligently folowe thy good counſeyll, and I enſure the, that thou haſt done more on me, with thy earneſt exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, than all the prieſtes and preachers that euer I heard in thys lande, &amp; thou
<pb facs="tcp:16259:39"/> arte alſo better learned and more experte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they this wyll I alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte of the before all men</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Geue not the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and prayſe vnto me, For al honour and prayſe be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>longeth to god onely, as god ſayth hymſelfe, I am the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, that is my name, I wyll geue myne honour to none other. Vnto hym wyll we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo aſſcribe, geue, and ſaye all honoure and righteouſnes, as the Prophet ſayth.<note place="margin">Dan. ix</note> Al ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor is thyne, and thou lorde arte righteous but we muſt be aſhamed, and al ſhame is oures. Therfore geue the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour vnto God, and not to me, nor to any creature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rapia.</speaker>
               <p>Honour and prayſe be
<pb facs="tcp:16259:40"/> vnto God for euermore, and I beſeeche the that it wyll pleaſe the to praye vnto god for me, that it wil pleaſe him to let me endure ſtedfaſtly to myne ende.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>The ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſaynt Iames teacheth vs that we ſhoulde pray one for another, that we myght all be ſaued, whiche I wyll alſo do truely for the, and for all men, do thou ſo lyke wyſe for me. It is now tyme, I muſt be gone, my hartely be loued ſyſter. The mercyfull God bleſſe the, and ſende the hys bleſſynge. The grace &amp; peace of oure Lorde Ieſu Chriſte, be with thy louin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge huſbande Simplicius, (vnto whome thou ſhalt pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nounce my harty commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:40"/> whan he cometh home) and with all thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milye, I committe the to the tuition of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>God thanke the my louin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſyſter, and God ſende the proſperite and health, that thou mayeſt come home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne in ſauetie, I feare, that I ſhall neuer ſe the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>I wyll (yf God permitte (come to the agayne ſhortely, fare well, the lorde be with the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia.</speaker>
               <p>And with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina</speaker>
               <p>But yet or euer I depart (for as muche as it cometh into my mynd) I wil geue the a ſhorte inſtructie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerninge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate of matrimony, which of late I learned at a ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16259:41"/> declared vpon a certayne place of ſaynt Ihons Goſpel whiche I truſte ſhall be no leſſe for thyne edifyenge and inſtruction, then that godly communication, which hath ben betwene vs hetherto. And the ſayd ſermon was grounded vpon this pece of ſcripture contayned in the ſeconde chapiter of ſaynte Ihon, and ſoundeth thus.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the wedding feast at Cana, featuring Jesus Christ (giving a blessing) and Mary at a table with two men and a woman, while a servant pours water from a bucket into one of five jars on the ground</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>Iohan. ij.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iohan. ij</note>THere was a mariage in Cana, a Cite of Galile, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:16259:41"/> the mother of Ieſus was the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. And Ieſus was called al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo and hys diſciples vnto the mariage. And when the wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne fayled, the mother of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſayd vnto hym. They ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue no wyne. Ieſus ſayd vnto her, woman, what haue I to do with the? myne houre is not yet come. His mother ſayd vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters. what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he ſayth vnto you, do it. And there were ſtondyng there, ſixe waterpottes of ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, after the maner of the purifyeng of the Iewes, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tainyng two or thre firkyns a pece. And Ieſus ſayd vnto them: fyll the waterpottes with water. And they filled them vp to the brym, and he ſayd vnto them, drawe oute
<pb facs="tcp:16259:42"/> nowe, and beare vnto the go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uernour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feaſt. And they bare it. When the ruler of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feaſte had taſted the water, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was tourned vnto wyne, &amp; knewe not whence it was, (but the miniſters which dre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we the water knewe) He cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the bryde grome, &amp; ſayde vnto hym. All men at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnynge, ſetforth good wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and when me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be dronke, then that whiche is worſe. But thou haſt kept backe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good wyne, vntil now. This beginnyng of miracles did Ieſus in Cana of Galile, &amp; ſhewed hys glory, &amp; his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples beleued in hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serap.</speaker>
               <p>Vvhat teacheth vs thys go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Thre poyntes, firſt that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16259:42"/> ſtate of matrimony is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of god. Secondely. An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the faith in Marie. Thirdly, an example of loue in Chriſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Howe knoweſt thou, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> matri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mony is the worke of god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Out of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, bothe of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and alſo of the newe, &amp; by experience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Vvhat ſayth the olde teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of matrimony?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>The olde teſtament decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that god did inſtitute, and ordeyne matrimony, in Paradyſe, in the tyme of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencye, before all ſynne, &amp; toke great diligence, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and labour about it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:16259:43"/>
               <p>Vvhat paynes dyd he take in it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gene. i.</note>Geneſ. i. it is wrytten, that the hygh Maieſtye of God, dyd fyrſt Counſel aboute the ſhapynge of man, ſayenge, Let vs make man, in oure Image after our lykenes,<note place="margin">Gene. ij and xviij Sapie. x Tob viij Eccleſi. xxxiv. 1. Cor xv</note> And God ſhope man, euen duſt from of the grounde, and breathed into hys noſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trelles the breathe of lyfe. After that he counſelled al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo aboute the ſhaping of the woman,<note place="margin">Gene. ij</note> ſayenge. It is not good that man ſhoulde be al one, we wyll make hym an helpe. And the lorde cauſed a ſlomber to fall vpon Adam. And he ſlept. And he toke o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of hys rybbes, and made it a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and broughte her
<pb facs="tcp:16259:43"/> vnto hym. Then ſayd Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Ec. xvij 1. Cor. xi</note> This is nowe a bone of my bones, and fleſhe of my flleſh She ſhall be called woman, becauſe ſhe was taken oute of man.<note place="margin">mat. xix Mar. x Eph. v i. Cor. v.</note> for this cauſe ſhal ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leaue hys father and hys mother, and ſhalbe ioyned with hys wyfe, and they ſhal become one fleſhe.<note place="margin">Gene. i.</note> And God bleſſed them, and ſayde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, Growe and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, and replenyſhe the earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Vvorketh god this worke yet ſtyll?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Yea verely, yet ſtyll, as chriſt ſayth Iohan v.<note place="margin">Iohan v</note> My father worketh hitherto and I wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke. God cauſeth not onely boyes, but alſo wenches to be borne, not for to ſinne har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:44"/> but for an honeſte and vertuous conuerſacion, and for the preſeruation &amp; mayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenaunce, of all mankynde. Nowe lyke as God prouyded vnto Adam hys wyfe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hys knowledge and hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe. Euen ſo doth he yet in theſe dayes brynge man and wyfe together, wonderfully without all theyr myndes &amp; thoughtes.<note place="margin">Pro. xix</note> As it is wrytten Prouerb. xix. Houſe &amp; ryches may a man haue by the heri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tage of elders, but a diſcrete woman is the gyfte of the Lorde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Vhat ſpeaketh the newe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament of matrimony?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina..</speaker>
               <p>The newe teſtament ſheweth that chriſt hath ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate of matrimony
<pb facs="tcp:16259:44"/> and that, he went with hys diſciples to the mariage in Cana of Galile, illuſtrynge theſame with a goodly mira<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cle, tournynge water into wyne. To ſignifye thereby, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he among faythfull maryed people wil alſo tourne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of trouble, in to wyne of ioye, yf they walke in a good conuerſacion, lyue according to theyr vocacion and eſtate, and do that thynge whiche is godly and ryght.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapi.</speaker>
               <p>Howe canſt thou knowe by experience that matrimony is the worke of god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>That there in is muche pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefullnes labour and vniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines, for ſuche are the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of god, that they ſeme
<pb facs="tcp:16259:45"/> alwayes vnto the olde Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſoure, bitter, &amp; heauy. But God hath ordeyned the ſame ſo, to thintent that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de not be ydel, and by the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſon ther of fall into euil ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full cogitacions, wordes, &amp; workes, but that he ſhoulde alwayes haue occaſion to worke and to do ſomthynge for to expel there by the euill thoughtes, wordes, &amp; dedes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Is then Idelnes ſuche an euyll thynge?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Idelnes, is an occaſion of many ſynnes and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, Sathan dyd no ſmall hurte to the Chriſtianite, when he dyd put into the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes heade, to forbidde matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monye
<pb facs="tcp:16259:45"/> vnto the ſpiritualtye for thorough ſo many ydell perſons hath he filled the Chriſtianite, with ſynnes &amp; abhominations, as Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and Gomorre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Is then labour ſuche a coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Yea forſoth, labour taketh awaye from man, many euil thoughtes, wordes &amp; dedes, it bringeth good occupieng, and kepeth hym healthfull. It bringeth to the table a hungry ſtomake, and to the bedde a wery body. Therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re doth meate and drynke ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uour wel vnto hym, and ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe is ſwete and acceptable vnto hym. And alſo ſuch one fulfilleth Goddes comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:46"/> where as he ſayth. In the ſweate of thy face ſhalt thou eate thy breade.<note place="margin">Gen. iij</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Vvhat muſt one do which ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth hym ſelfe into the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of matrimony?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>He muſt haue a reſpecte to thre thynges, to fayth, loue, and the croſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Vvherfore to fayth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>That he beleue, that matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is the worke of god, &amp; that god is hys good father, which can and wyl prouyde hym of an honeſt mate. And when that is done, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt he alſo thynke no further vpon other, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tente him
<pb facs="tcp:16259:46"/> ſelfe with her, whiche god hath ſent hym,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>But howe and yf there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen any tediouſnes in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Then muſt euery one thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke thus. Beholde, god hath geuen me thys fellowe, he knoweth well ynough, what is good &amp; profitable for me. yf he had geuen me another it myght peraduenture be nore to my hynderau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, then to my furtheraunce. The wyll of the lorde be done vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me. Truely where ſuche thoughtes are, there can it not go amyſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Vvherfore to the loue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:16259:47"/>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>He muſt knowe that the Eſtate of matrimony is an eſtate of loue and peace, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therein the one muſt ſerue, helpe, and counſeyl y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, and that there be nothynge but ſeruyce, helpe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te betwene them ſelues and after that, towardes theyr children, familye, &amp; all men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Howe betwene them ſelues?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Maryed folkes muſt be pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aceable, frendly, &amp; agreyng, one with another, not deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge one another, but be true one to another faithful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſerue and ſuccour one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in proſperite and in aduerſitye, in ſickenes and
<pb facs="tcp:16259:47"/> in health euen as God doth ſend it. for God made not the woman of the mannes hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, becauſe ſhe ſhould not be mayſter, nor yet of the fete, that ſhe ſhoulde not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lye vnder fote.<note place="margin">Gen. ij.</note> But of hys ſyde that ſhe ſhoulde be the mans helper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Howe towardes the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and familie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>When god ſendeth them children or familye, that thei bryng vp the ſame to the lau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, honour, &amp; prayſe of god, to the helpe, commoditie, &amp; conforte of theyr neyghbour yea for the welthe of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le communalte. And there ſhal they fynde bothe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des
<pb facs="tcp:16259:48"/> full of good workes, yea all the workes of loue, whiche God hath commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, may they ſhewe vpon theyr chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and familye. God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of that hous, good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed folkes, a holy hoſpitall an electe monaſtery, yea a kyngdome of Ioye, Paradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and heauen, he geueth his bleſſynge, and all goodnes, health and ſaluacion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Howe towardes the croſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Maryed folkes, muſt knowe that God hath layde a heuy croſſe vpon the ſtate of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, bothe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Vvhiche is the croſſe of the man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:16259:48"/>
               <p>God ſayd vnto Adam.<note place="margin">Gen. iij</note> Becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe thou haſte herkened vnto the voyce of thy wyfe, &amp; haſt eaten of the tree concerning the whiche I commaund d the ſaieng, thou ſhalt not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of it curſed be the groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de for thy ſake, in ſorrowe ſhalt thou eate of it all the dayes of thy lyfe. Thorne al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo and thyſtle ſhal it cauſe to growe vnto the. In the ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of thy face, ſhalt thou eate thy breade.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Whiche is the croſſe of the woman?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>God ſayde vnto Eua,<note place="margin">Gen. iij</note> becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe thou haſt herkened vnto the ſerpente, and haſte ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the fruytes concernin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge the whiche I commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the, that thou ſhouldeſt not
<pb facs="tcp:16259:49"/> eate of it. I wyll multiplye thy ſorowe and thy concey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng. In ſorrowe ſhalt thou brynge forth thy children, &amp; thou ſhalt ſtoupe before thy huſbande, and he ſhal haue the rule of the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Is there any conforte in thys Croſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>yes. By the croſſe of the man is this conforte contayned. In the ſweate of thy face ſhalt thou eate thy breade, tyll thou be tourned agayn into the grounde, out of the whiche thou waſt taken. As though he woulde ſaye. The croſſe ſhall be temporal, and ſhal laſte no longer, then whyleſt thou lyueſt. Alſo it
<pb facs="tcp:16259:49"/> is but layed vpon the body, and not vpon the ſoule.<note place="margin">Gen. iij</note> By the croſſe of the woman ſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth thys conſolacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thou ſhalt bryng forth children, albeit with ſorrowe, &amp; ſaynt ſaynt Paule ſayth. i. Tim. ij.<note place="margin">i. Tim. ij</note> The woman was deceaued and brought the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on into the worlde, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtondyng thorough bearing of children ſhe ſhal be ſaued, yf ſhe continue, in faythe, &amp; loue, and holynes with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Is the worde of god alſo in the lyfe of matrimony?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Not onely the worde of god, but alſo the commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ordinaunce, and bleſſyng of
<pb facs="tcp:16259:50"/> god, an honeſt lyfe, a good lyfe, a good conſcience, and hope of eternall lyfe. In the lyfe of the wicked, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge elles, then the work, commaundement and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of the Deuyll, theyr owne wyll, deſtourbyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly commaundementes, an vngracious ſhameful ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, an euil conſcience, and ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pectacion of eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion. The maried can ſheppe forth bodely before god, and reioyce of theyr eſtate with a good conſcience, I defie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ſtates of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiritualte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they dare be ſo bolde, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to open their mouthes before god, but they muſt be confounded and become do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be before god, for they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not
<pb facs="tcp:16259:50"/> alledge one lettere out of the holy ſcripture, whereby thei myght confirme or defende their eſtate. yf the popes try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple crowne, the Cardinalles broade hatte, the Biſſhoppes infula, the freares hode, the prieſtes ſhauen crowne, and the Nonnes clare, had ſuch a reioyſinge and grounde in the ſcripture, as the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s keuerchief, and the begging bagge of the ſpiritualte, as the ſpade or pickare of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. good lorde, howe would they boaſte, crye and reioyce, but Chriſt hath preuented theyr boaſting, &amp; ſtandeth there, &amp; ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. xv</note> In vayn they worſhip me, teaching doctrines, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che are nothyng, but me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes preceptes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:16259:51"/>
               <p>Where by is the fayth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued in Marye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ioha. iij</note>Vvhen the wyne fayled, the mother of Ieſue ſayde vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hym. They haue no wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. The good mother careth for the geſtes, and woulde fayne that al thynges were well, and done honeſtly, and yet doth ſhe not praye with expreſſed wordes. for ſhe thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght, it nedeth not to praye. He is ſo good of hymſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll helpe, whan he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that there is lacke. And this is alſo the nature of fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the, to aduenture al thinges vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mercifulnes of god.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>But what anſwerdyd Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte geue her?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:16259:51"/>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>He ſent her away vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſayde vnto her,<note place="margin">Ioha. iii</note> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, what haue I to do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the, myne houre is not yet come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Vvhat doth Mary then, doth ſhe leaue it thus?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>No, ſhe ſayth nowe firſt of al to the miniſters, whatſoeuer he ſayth vnto you do it. So certayne and ſure is ſhe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe beleueth, that her welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued ſonne Chriſte wyll not ſuffer her to lacke, and euen as ſhe beleueth ſo cometh it to paſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Vvhat ſhall we learne he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:16259:52"/>
               <p>Vvhen it ſemeth vnto vs in our prayer, that god wyl not heare vs, then may we not yet deſpayre or ceaſſe, but we muſt ſtyll go forwarde &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſte. for vnder ſuch a tacitur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite is a ſure conforte hydde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnder ſuche, naye lyeth a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, yea, for ſo doth god worke he helpeth no rather, then when a man thinketh, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all confort and ſuccour is gone. Therfore is he called. The ryght helper in neceſſities, which helpeth in due ſeaſon</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Vvhere by is the loue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued in Chriſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>That he prouydeth here ſuche good wyne, at thys feaſt, he hath ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
<pb facs="tcp:16259:52"/> by this example, that he wyl not put thoſe in any neceſſite, whiche geue them ſelues, at his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, into the ſtate of matri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mony, beleue and truſte in hym, and followe theyr vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacyon, nor yet leaue them confortles. For beholde, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wyne fayled he made of water good wyne. Euen ſo, yf men dotruely and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly call vpon hym matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, he wyll alſo take awaye all maner of penuryes, he knoweth well ynough that in matrimony fayleth, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thynges, nowe meate &amp; drynke, nowe rayment and ſhoes. Therfore, yf the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed do that thing which plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God, and ſeke fyrſte the
<pb facs="tcp:16259:53"/> kyngdome of god, he wyl ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer forſake them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>Geue examples of the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iuſtina.</speaker>
               <p>Who fedde the Patriarche Iacob, when he went ouer Iordan with hys ſtaffe, and came agayne with moche pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ople, children, cattell &amp; goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des?<note place="margin">Geneſ. xxxij</note> Gene. xxxij. Vho fed Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeph? whan he was ſolde of hys brethren, became he not by the grace of God, a lorde ouer al Egypte? Vvho fed the children of Iſrael in the wildernes forthy yeres? Vvho prouyded here good wyne? yea, who fedeth the hole worlde with all creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res? Doth not God it? True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly noman nedeth to refuſe
<pb facs="tcp:16259:53"/> matrimonye or to abſtayne from it for hunger or penuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſake. But let him take the matter in hande, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the feare of God, and do accordyng as hys office or occupation requyreth, let hym worke hys occupation in the name of the Lorde, put hys truſt in God, &amp; wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ryghteouſly in the ſyghte of hys neyghboure, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall he fynde of a trueth, that god wyl holde on hys ſyde ſo moche as he did with Iacob Ioſeph, and with the Bryde and Brydegrome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serapia.</speaker>
               <p>But what ſayeſt thou, of eatynge drynkynge, deckin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and trimmynge, pypyng, playenge and daunſyng, is it
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16259:54"/> the worde of god in the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. The elders toke it for a great earneſt matter, name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, that they fetched there y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſyng of God, and the ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plication of the Chriſten con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which in dede is very neceſſary and requiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, in this eſtate. And whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer taketh vpon hym the ſtate of matrimony, nedeth well the bleſſynge of god, &amp; the common prayers of the congregation. Seyng the deuyll neuer reſteth here, but attempteth all maner of wayes, for to ſtirre vp mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che miſchief, and calamitie with infidelyte, aduoutrye, vnclenlynes, and all maner of wickednes. All whiche
<pb facs="tcp:16259:54"/> thinges God the father, &amp; oure lorde Ieſus Chriſte, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and wyll hynder, and let, vnto whome be lande &amp; prayſe for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:55"/>
            <head>¶A fruteful Predication or Sermon of D. Mart. Luth. concernynge matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, vpon this Texte, in the Epiſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, in the xiij. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Wedlocke is to be had in honour, amonge all men, and the bedde vndefyled. As for hoorekepers and aduou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, God ſhall iudge them.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ben eſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, alſo amonge the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athen.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He eſtate of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimony hath alwayes ben taken among diſcrete &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea alſo amonge the heathen,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:55"/> for an honourable and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable lyfe, for reaſonable &amp; vertuous people, haue euen of very nature a delyte in it, when they ſee, that two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonnes which are coupled in mariage, lyue together ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly and in vnite, brynge vp theyr children in the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of God, kepe them to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous nurtour, &amp; honeſty. And that the one ſuccoureth the other in neceſſities and aydeth hym with worde and dede, and wherwith ſo euer he can. Contrarywyſe, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men lyue, withoute the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of matrimony, in vnclen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, ſynne, and ſhame. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber not theyr childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor brynge them vp in good nourtour, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth
<pb facs="tcp:16259:56"/> this waye, and the other that waye, lyke noughtye packes, hauing no true loue nor faythfulnes together. Suche a diſſolute lyfe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, of all reaſonable and honeſt men, euen of nature, wicked, and very pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and rawe pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ople de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpyſe matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</note>Notwithſtondyng menſe right well, howe the yonger ſorte, and the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people falleth awaye, and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſtate of matrimony as an heauy intollerable burthen. And ſuche wilde, ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reles perſons, wyll alwayes more loue the diſſolute and fre lyfe, then ſuche a payne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, vertuous, and laudable lyfe in wedlocke. Howe be it plages and punyſhmentes
<pb facs="tcp:16259:56"/> ouertake them nowe a day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es very ſore. for beſides that that ſuch perſones without wedlocke, pollute themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues with ſynnes wilfully, &amp; cauſe God to be enemy vnto themſelues, they are alſo pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſſhed with bodely plages, that not onely money and goodes, doth waſte away by ſuche people, but alſo they muſt paye for it in their ſkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. For in ſuche filthy lyuin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, reigne many maner of diſeaſes and plages, ſomety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me open ſhame, and reuilyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, ſomtyme alſo murther, &amp; other calamityes.</p>
            <p>Of ſuche examples is the worlde full, whereby god ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth a ſpecial earneſt, that he wyll haue wedlock kepte
<pb facs="tcp:16259:57"/> pure, and vndeſpiſed. But whereas ſome tyme ſuche te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poral correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s followe not. And god permitteth the wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked perſons, to go after their owne wyll, and to abyde in reputacion, and healthfull body, &amp; great goodes, Euen there is ſurely a worſe tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to be attended, namely, the wrath and indignation, of God in the worlde to come and the euerlaſtynge dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Some deſpyſe matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, becauſe of great holynes</note>Lyke as nowe the madde yonge worlde abhorreth ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimony for ſuche free, wyll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full lyues ſake. Euen ſo is it manifeſte of the other par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, that the Deuyll hath blyndedſome in ſuche wyſe, that they, of mere holynes,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:57"/> lyke as the other of mere wilfulnes, haue deſpiſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, and choſen a diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute lyfe without wedlocke. Accordyng as Saynt Paule hath prophecyed.<note place="margin">i. Ti. iiij</note> i. Timo. iiij That it ſhall come ſo farre, that certeyne ſpirites of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour vnder the pretenſe of great holynes, ſhall forbidde matrimony. As we ſe by the Pope, and all hys Byſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, Prieſtes, freares &amp; Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whiche forſwere matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and wyll be called ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall people, becauſe they lyue without wedlocke and lyue not in a carnal ſtate, as they iudge matrimony. But in an angelicall or ſpirituall ſtate, and haue called them ſelues alone ſpiritual for this
<pb facs="tcp:16259:58"/> cauſe, as though, thei which lyue in the ſtate of matrimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, myght not be ſpiritual al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo, as well as they?</p>
            <p>This is the occaſion, becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe that matrimony is ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and hath no ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gard before the world. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore haue the popes bleſſed, or they of the ſpiritualtie, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſed ſuche ſlyghte common lyfe, and haue taken ſome ſpeciall thynge before them, whiche myght be more regar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, then that a Citeſen ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at home with hys wyfe fyndeth hys children and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie with ſoure labour, and doth ſuche lyke thynges, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to hys vocation. For thys is the nature of the worlde, whatſoeuer is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:58"/> the ſame doth ſhe not regarde. Agayn whatſoeuer is ſtraunge and not common the ſame doth euery man co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet to haue. No man doth counte this for a ſpecial thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, that the ſunne ſhyneth euery daye.<note place="margin">Exod. x</note> But whan the thicke darkenes continued ſo longe in Egypte, then did they learne vndoubtedly, &amp; fynde fulwel, that the ſunne and the brightnes thereof, is a glorious thynge, and a fayre great benefite. Alſo we counte it for no ſpecial grace when it rayneth.<note place="margin">i. Reg. xvij.</note> But when there came no rayne in the kyngdome of Iſraell, in the tyme of Elias, for the ſpace of thre yeres, and a halfe, then dyd they learne, that
<pb facs="tcp:16259:59"/> it was a great benefite.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo happeneth it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the holy ſtate of matrimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, amonge the Papiſtes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, becauſe it is ſuche a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtate, that euery plowe man may come to it. Therfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re haue the popes Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altye deſpiſed ſuche a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyfe, and haue inuented and taken vpon them, a ſpeciall and ſundry lyfe, that myght ſeme to be of greater eſtima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, before the people. As Nicolaus de lyra ſayth vpon the xij. chapiter of Daniel.<note place="margin">Vpon the .xij Chapit. of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte.</note> That Antichriſte ſhal not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garde the loue of women for thys cauſe, that he maye make to hym ſelfe a greater apearaunce of holynes. But what good enſueth thereof,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:59"/> it is euident. In ſo muche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by reaſon we ſhoulde learne by theyr example, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> matry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is a glorious and an holy lyfe. for as muche as they are punyſhed with dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers abhominable and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryble ſynnes, euen becauſe that they contemne wedloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. for they haue in no point ſo hole, agaynſte all reaſon, and nature miſuſed themſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues as in this poynt.</p>
            <p>For as muche nowe,<note place="margin">Vvher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary to wryte of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</note> as the ſtate of matrimony, is abhorred of the workemon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers or ypocrytes, and rawe people in the world, &amp; is cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, either for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vnho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, or els for a hard &amp; ſtraight lyfe. So is it neceſſarye,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:60"/> to obtayne out of the worde of god, a right vnderſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of matrimony, and to teache agaynſt ſuche falſe opinions what god ſpeaketh of the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe of matrimony. To thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that firſt the yonge people may learne, wherfore matri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mony is to be taken. After that, that they may knowe alſo, howe they ſhall behaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues therein. So that men abide not onely by that that the worlde ſpeaketh &amp; holdeth thereof with her madde ſainctes. But that whiche god and hys worde, ſpeketh therof. Albe it, that the holy ſcripture is full of ſuch ſentences, where in the ſtate of matrimony is highly prayſed. yet wyl we neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles
<pb facs="tcp:16259:60"/> nowe at thys tyme abyde by this ſayenge. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre. xiij, whiche ſoundeth thus.</p>
            <p>Vvedlocke is to be had in honour, amonge all men, &amp; the bed vndefyled. As for hoore kepers, and aduoute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, God ſhall iudge them.</p>
            <p>This ſentence is good and ſhorte, whiche beſydes that,<note place="margin">The true me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>anyng of the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Heb. xiij</note> that ſhe ſpeaketh greatly in the prayſe of matrimony, &amp; threateneth thoſe ſore, that deſpiſe matrimony, maketh alſo an after thynkyng, why and wherfore he wyll haue this matrimony had in ſuch honour. Notwitbſtandynge that it is ſo deſpyſed and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred in the worlde. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanyng of thys ſentence is
<pb facs="tcp:16259:61"/> this. That wedlock is an ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nourable, goodly and coſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thynge. To thintent that all they which are the rein, ſhoulde holde and counte theyr lyues, for a noble, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and goodly gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhynge. Appeare it before the worlde as it wyll, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde ſpeake of it what ſhe wyll.</p>
            <p>Thys godly iudgement of matrimony, as euery man mayſe, ſoundeth farre other wyſe than the worlde hath imagined thereof. for yf the worlde dyd counte matrimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſo precious and honoura<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, ſhe woulde not flee from it, and lyue without wedloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. But lyke as men haſte them ſelues thitherwarde
<pb facs="tcp:16259:61"/> where they loke for ſome good coſtely thynges. Euen ſo ſhoulde they alſo ſnatche after wedlock, with loue and ioye, and not defende them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo from it with hande and fote as the wilde dieres agaynſt the dogges. for that the worlde doth ſo ſpurne at kycke at it, now ymaginyng thys, now that is altogether a ſygne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe neyther kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth Goddes worde, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng matrimonye, nor yet beleueth the ſame, or els ſhe woulde applye her ſelues a lytel otherwyſe to it.</p>
            <p>But what the occaſion is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the worlde thus ſpurneth at the ſtate of matrimony is partly touched before, That noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil gladly be bounde,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:62"/> and feareth that it myght ſuccede vnluckely. Therfore ſhall it be neceſſary that we alſo here in this parte, ſeke, and declare the occaſyon or cauſe: wherfore the holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture boaſteth and prayſeth wedlock ſo, highly &amp; honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably. And ſpecially ſhoulde the Chriſtians well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and ponder ſuche occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and cauſes. To thin te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that they myght mete with the worlde, and be able to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fende matrimony agaynſte the euyll ſpeakynges of the worlde.</p>
            <p>So is nowe the firſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that it maye be proued by the worde of god, that ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimony was inſtituted of God hymſelfe, and planted
<pb facs="tcp:16259:62"/> in oure nature. Accordynge as the ſame is clearly deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the fyrſt Boke of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And Chriſte ſpeaketh in the newe Teſtament. Mat. xix. He that made man at the beginnynge, made them man and woman, and ſayd. for thys cauſe ſhall a man le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aue father &amp; mother, &amp; ſhall cleaue vnto hys wyfe. Agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſayth he, whatſoeuer co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth together by the waye of matrimony, the ſame hath God coupled together &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Let thys be vnto euerye man a glorious and greate reioyſynge, and prayſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimony, that it is not a wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke of man wrought by hys owne wyll. But the worke of God. vnto the whiche god
<pb facs="tcp:16259:63"/> hymſelfe hath created man. So that a couple of wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded folkes, before the face of God, with al trueth may bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſte them ſelues of this, that they are in an eſtate, which is acceptable vnto God, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che God hymſelfe hath inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in nature. and whyleſt they lyue in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che eſtate, that they lyue in the worke, yea alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and proper pleaſure or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyte of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyſe of their ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te before God</note>This reioyſyng hath not the Pope nor hys heape. For they can ſhewe no where, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lyue withoute wedlocke. Vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then the contrary par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te followeth, whyleſt they continue withoute wedloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:63"/> that they lyue withoute and agaynſte the worde, wil commaundement, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of god, but in theyr own wyll, which neuer can pleaſe God. Therfore when thei ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue aduerſite, euen as thei do deſerue, then is it vnpoſſible that they can haue the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, which the wedded men haue, whiche can admony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe God in all maner of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities and troubles and ſaye.</p>
            <p>O Lorde god,<note place="margin">The prayer of the maryed vnto God.</note> thys &amp; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aduerſite preſſeth me. And thou knoweſt, that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che trouble happeneth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to me and cometh vpon me, euen in theſame ſtate, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thou dyddeſt ſhape and
<pb facs="tcp:16259:64"/> inſtitute in Paradyſe with man. Therfore helpe, that we in this life inſtituted, ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pen, and entretayned by the, may be deliuered of this and that trouble, and aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitie &amp;c. With ſuche a prayer dare the maryed men come before God, where as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lyue in their owne deuo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion contrary to the worde and wil of God, and therfore they loke for no conforte, nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther can they praye a ryght vnto God.</p>
            <p>Therfore when the Pope, and hys vnmaried ſorte, lau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and prayſe muche theyr monkerie and Celibate lyfe. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laude and prayſe thou moche more thys lyfe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, whereon hangeth
<pb facs="tcp:16259:64"/> thys gloryous name &amp; tittel, that it is a godly lyfe, ſhapen &amp; comuaunded of God, and hys worde, whiche no freare nor prieſt ſhal be able at any tyme to boaſte of his Celiba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te lyfe.</p>
            <p>Thys is nowe the fyrſt, &amp; alſo the greateſt occaſyon, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wedlocke, as the text ſayth, is to be had in honoure. for as there is no thynge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute nor aboue God, euen ſo can there alſo be nothynge more excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nor better vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, then that whiche he hymſelfe dyd ſhape and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne. As the texte maketh mention in the fyrſte boke of Moyſes.<note place="margin">Gene. i.</note> And God ſawe eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry thyng that he had made, and beholde it was exceding
<pb facs="tcp:16259:65"/> good. Amonge theſe ſhapen thynges which were all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedynge good, is alſo wedloc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke. The celebate lyfe is not amonge them, but the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll hath inuented it, yf me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyl holde it for a goddes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce, and compel the people thereto, as the Pope doth.</p>
            <p>The other cauſe is, that god hath not onely inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted matrimonye.<note place="margin">God hath ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially bleſſed matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</note> But alſo he hath geuen his bleſſyng, therevnto. The ſame bleſſing ſtandeth not onely barely in that, that god geueth childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for there be alſo children bor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne oute of wedlocke. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god hath a delyte and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the ryght children, &amp; in the hole confederation, &amp; geueth grace, that they be
<pb facs="tcp:16259:65"/> well brought vp, well nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhed and preſerued. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſetteth the .Cxxviij.<note place="margin">Pſalm. Cxxviij</note> pſal me alſo this among the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſynges of the godfearynge people which lyue in wedloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. That they eate of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of their handes, and ſhall ſe theyr childers chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. That is, godfearynge people lyuinge in wedlocke ſhal haue this bleſſynge, to theyr ſuſtentation and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that they ſhal remayne and proſpere. Contrary to the whiche, in the Celibate lyfe, money and goodes va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe and waſte awaye, and all maner of calamitie folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth.</p>
            <p>Thys ſhoulde alſo by reaſon moue vs, that we myght
<pb facs="tcp:16259:66"/> gette luſt and loue towardes thys ſtate,<note place="margin">Vvher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re is ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in wedloc littel proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and helth.</note> ſeynge we fynde therein not onely the wyl of god, but alſo al maner of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynges. And there muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des be ſmal felicitie, &amp; health loked for, amonge thoſe that deſpyſe ſuche conforte and promyſe of God, and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re theyr fre and wylful lyfe. It is alſo to be feared, leſte the wrath of God myght be ſo kyndled agaynſte thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do long continue in ſuche de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpiſynge, that although thei ſhould at the laſt geue them ſelues to the ſtate of matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, they ſhoulde neyther haue proſperite nor helth. Euen as it cometh to paſſe oftentymes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men through vngratiouſnes and other
<pb facs="tcp:16259:66"/> vnhappynes in youth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wedlocke deſerue &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, that they haue but fewe good daies in wedlocke, and that bothe the woman and the children fare amiſſe. for as it is mentioned before, God wil execute ſuche iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment vpon the ſtate of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, that all they ſhall be punyſſhed, that lyue in vnclenlynes, and geue occa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of offence. Therfore ſhal the yong people prepare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues by tymes towardes it, and kepe themſelues in the feare of God, and in clen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynes, To thintent that thei themſelues do not hynder &amp; kepe backe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſyng, which God hath ioygned with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:67"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ateſt ſainetes that euer ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued (fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte) were waryed</note>The thyrde cauſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke is to be had in honour, is this, that in thys ſtate for the mooſt parte the greateſt ſainctes haue ended theyr ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues, as the hole old and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we teſtament withneſſeth. But yf thou wilt knowe, why they haue all lyued in wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, I can ſhewe thy no better nor ſurer reaſon, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that all Godly men, haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ordered and kepte themſelues after the wyll and worde of god. And for as moche as god hymſelfe hath inſtituted and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Matrimony. So haue they as obedyent Perſons, which had nede of ſuche or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of god, geuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:16259:67"/> willingly and gladly into the ſtate of matrimony for gods and their nedes ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. Not regardyng, that the worlde and the common pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ople loued more the fre and wilfull lyfe.</p>
            <p>Nowe, this is not a ſmal re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioyſynge, that whoſoeuer is coupled in wedlocke, may ſay with a fre and bolde con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience, that he is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſame ſtate, wherin the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes, Prophetes, the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Apoſtles and other ſainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes moſt commonly haue ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, whereas contrarywy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe the celibate lyfe, was fyrſt begonne of certayne he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>retykes, becauſe they would make them ſelues thereby
<pb facs="tcp:16259:68"/> a ſundry pretenſe and colour of holynes.<note place="margin">The po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of al hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſye.</note> And was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde confirmed of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe as of the Archefather of all hypocriſye, and boaſted for an holy lyfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He that wil be a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and can not lyue cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte, ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte to marye.</note>For as concernyng Iohn the Baptiſte, and other ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che lyke, which for the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauens ſake, as Chriſte doth call it, dyd ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues from wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, it hath a ſundry mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng. We ſpeake here in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, of all them, that wyll be Chriſtians, and can not lyue chaſte out of wedlocke. Vnto thoſe it is very confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table that they ſe before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> examples of ſo many greate ſaynctes, which haue all ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in wedlocke, and haue
<pb facs="tcp:16259:68"/> gone before vs in this holy ordre. Truely this is a great prayſe to wedlocke. for who woulde not rather be found among ſuche a companye of holy men, in lyke lyfe eſtate and conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with them, then by the Pope, and hys hole flocke, whiche in thys &amp; in other affayres lyue ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly agaynſt Goddes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, and the exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples of hys ſaynctes.</p>
            <p>The fourth occaſyon, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wedlocke is to be had in honour and reuerence, and not in contempte, is this. That without wedlocke,<note place="margin">To ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oute wedloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not without ſynne.</note> we can not well lyue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute ſynne, and in a good Conſcience. for thus ſayth Chriſte, wheras he ſpeaketh
<pb facs="tcp:16259:69"/> of them that lyue withoute wedlocke.<note place="margin">mat. xix i. cor. vij</note> Al men can not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehende thys ſayenge. And ſaint Paule commaundeth, To auoyde fornication, let euery man haue hys wyfe. For through the original ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne is the nature of man wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kened and deſtroyed in ſuch wyſe, that very fewe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of wedlocke ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyue in a good conſcience. Seing then that matrimony is a remedy whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che god himſelf thereto hath ſhapen and ordeyned, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as his worde declareth that we ſtande in a good con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience, and maye lyue chaſt. Vvho wil be ſo rude &amp; vndiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete that he wil repute this eſtate vnholy, as the Pope doth?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:69"/>
            <p>But as it is aboue ſpecify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he hath receyued hys re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde. And to thintent that euery man ſhould eſteme the papiſtes for holy menne, thei haue forſworne Matrimony and fal thereby into the gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ateſt ſynne, and ſhame, in ſo moche that of their abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable lyuynge the hole worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de doth ſyng and ſaye. Thei are well ſerued, why do they ſo frowardly deſpiſe the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god? And we muſt alſo for this cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe haue wedlocke in honour and in hygh reputacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and thanke god highly for thys meane, whiche ſerueth vs for thys ende, that we pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute not ourſelues through horedome and ſuche other
<pb facs="tcp:16259:70"/> vnclenlynes, and ſo fal into the fearfull Iudgement of God, whereof we ſhal entre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate more hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke is ful of good workes</note>The fyrſte and laſte cauſe is thys. That wedlocke alſo therfore is to be had in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, becauſe it is ſuche a ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe, which, yf it be kept accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, is thoroughout full of good workes. for euen the loue which is betwene man and wyfe, is one of the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all good workes, whiche God hath commaunded and left remaynynge in nature, and helpeth with hys holy Gooſt that we do perfourme them a ryght, &amp; fainte not in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfore exhorteth alſo the holy Saynt Paule to ſuche loue whereas he ſayth. ye
<pb facs="tcp:16259:70"/> menne loue youre wyues, &amp; be not bitter vnto them. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſ. iij.<note place="margin">Colo. iij Ephe. v</note> And to the Epheſians in the .v. menne ought to lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue their wyues as their own bodies. Therfore whoſoeuer taketh ſure holde on ſuch lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, &amp; ſuffereth neyther noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome luſtes, wrath, nor anye other thinge to tourne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe awaye from it, doth a ryght good worke and accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table vnto god. for here is hys worde, which commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth the thys thynge. Thou ſhalt loue thy wyfe, and not loue flightely.<note place="margin">mat. xix</note> But as chriſt repeteth the ſame agayne in the goſpell. for thys cauſe ſhall a man leaue father &amp; mother, and cleane vnto his wyfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:71"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue is a goddes ſeruyce.</note>Vvhere are nowe the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefull Papiſtes, whiche ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>horre wedlocke as a carnall eſtate, as though God could not be ſerued in hys kynde of lyfe. Notwithſtandyng that the loue, without the which wedlocke can not endure, is a greater and hyer goddes ſeruice, which god, as we he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are, requyreth ſo earneſtly of vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue of the paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes theyr children is alſo a Gods ſeruyce.</note>Moreouer the loue and faythfulnes, whiche the Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rentes beſtowe vppon theyr children, namely, that they nouryſſhe, clothe and bryng them vp in labour and in the feare of god, kepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge, take heede to them &amp; kepe them in theyr ſickenes, watching, liſting, laieng, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:71"/> waſhing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer there is more of ſuche lyke, is alſo a coſtely worke &amp; acceptable vnto god, whiche the maryed muſt vſe and do dayly and hourely, &amp; almoſt euery moment. Nowe ſhould we remember a ryght and lerne, ſuch oure owne lyfe &amp; conuerſation, that theſe are before God mere good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. Then ſhould we not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly be ſo moche the luſtier to matrimony, and to ſuch wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, although they are alſo paynefull. But alſo pacien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confortabler, and bolder although ſomtyme it proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not all of the beſte. for yf the maryed remember and ponder theyr eſtate, and theyr lyfe a right, and
<pb facs="tcp:16259:72"/> ordre themſelues godly the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein, then muſt nedes theyr hertes, eyes, handes, &amp; fete ſticke full of good and holye workes euery houre.</p>
            <p>But there lyeth that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchief, where of I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before, that bycauſe the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe workes are ſo generall, &amp; ſmal, they are not regarded. Agayne, whatſoeuer apea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth glorious, and braggeth furth boldely although in it ſelfe it be not worth a ſtrawe yet is it taken for honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and greate. As we ſee by the Popes ceremonyes, and hys goddes ſeruice, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng that the leaſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke in wedlocke, is better in it ſelfe, then all theyr goddes ſeruice. for in wedlocke do
<pb facs="tcp:16259:72"/> men abyde in the worde and commaundement of God. And god wyll that the one ſhall gladly ſerue the other euen from the herte.</p>
            <p>This is done in wedlocke without ceaſſynge.<note place="margin">The ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are good workes</note> yf a child be ſicke, then are the elders ſick and ſory for hym, yf the man be ſicke, then is the wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe encombred euen ſo ſore as though it were her owne ſmarte, or diſeaſe. There is the diligence, care, faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes and loue mooſt pureſt and from the botome of the herte, and it is not tedyous vnto them, for they delyte &amp; long ſtyll after thys howe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one myght conſeyll, helpe, &amp; amende the other, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the aduerſitye. Again
<pb facs="tcp:16259:73"/> wheras it ſuccedeth proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly in trauaylyng of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, or otherwyſe in theyr ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne danger, or neceſſite of the children. There is a harty, pure, and perfecte ioye. It ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not go ſo wel with the one but the other reioyſeth of it euen at the herte and wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vnto hym moche more. Vvho wilſaye nowe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hertes do agree ſo good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly together, in ioye, and in heuynes, that there are not mere good workes of loue? Contrarywyſe in the Celi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate lyfe doth God neyther delite in loue, nor yet in woo. Althoughe in it ſelfe it is a ſtrawen loue, whiche euery houre is broken and rent a ſunder of one worde onely,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:73"/> when the one doth but loke awrye vpon the other.</p>
            <p>Theſe good workes of wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>locke remayne at home in the houſſe,<note place="margin">The ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creteper ſones to all eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> among them that be maried, and their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. After them followe fyrſt of al, the ryght great good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, that oute of thys eſtate, as out of a well ſprynge, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me all maner of perſonnes, by whome laude and people are gouerned and defended, the churches prouyded of pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>achers, and other miniſters and all offyces in the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and in the kyngdome of oure Lorde Chriſte are exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
            <p>Forſeyng ſpecially in wedloc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are nouryſhed
<pb facs="tcp:16259:74"/> and brought vp to the feare honoure, and glorye of god. So muſt it nedes be graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that wedlocke is occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and beginnynge of all ſuche benefites. Notwithſtandyng that many wilfull perſons do growe vp amonge them. The faulte thereof is not in wedlocke, but in thoſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vngodly perſonnes that wyl not order themſelues in wedlocke, accordyng to their bounden duetye, for whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doth begynne it in the name of god, he ſhall alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpere in bryngyng vp of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and in other thynges.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>locke is much la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d trauayl.</note>But that men will ſaye. In wedlocke are many ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of encombraunces, ſorro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes, dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, &amp; heuineſſes,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:74"/> from the which men ſhall be free out of wedlocke, where as euery man hath no more to care for, but hys owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by only. Nowe let it be ſo, yet ought thys occaſion to feare no Chriſten man from the ſtate of matrimony. For firſt although thou wereſt vnma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryed. yet for all that ſhalt thou not eſcape all fre, for thou muſt neuertheleſſe aue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture and ſuffer all maner of aduerſityes. Whan any hyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deraunce happeneth vnto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, ſomtyme in thy body, and lyfe ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme in thyne honour and goodes. And ſuche a croſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ſhal be ſo moche to heuyer for the, yf thou be out of wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>locke and alone, as the holy ſcripture ſayth. Wo be vnto
<pb facs="tcp:16259:75"/> the man, which is alone, for yf he fall, there is no man to helpe hym vp agayne.</p>
            <p>Secondarely. All be it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in wedlocke there is more daunger ſorrowe and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then elles where yet ought not to matrimony for thys cauſe to be deſpyſed &amp; eſchued. For it is profitable &amp; good for vs, that God cometh vpon vs with hys croſſe, and that we be proued al maner of waies, for oute of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and probacion, do we ſtande in great dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. Vve waxe ſturdy, and contrary to the worde of God colde &amp; ſlouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to praier and other good workes, for as muche nowe as wedlocke it doth ful now with the woman, nowe with
<pb facs="tcp:16259:75"/> the children, nowe with the familye,<note place="margin">wedloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke is the ſcoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hous of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</note> nowe with the occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyenge, and other al maner of neceſſities &amp; perilles wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>locke is vnto the Chriſtians as a Scoole, wherein they are godly inſtructed, that in tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and aduerſitie they faynt not, nor be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raged. But open theyr her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to god, pray &amp; deſyre help</p>
            <p>This is alſo a good worke,<note place="margin">wedlock cauſeth to praye and to truſt in God.</note> whereunto wedlocke geueth occaſyon very often, for euen for thys cauſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; calamite falleth in wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>locke, the maryed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yf thei be elles godfearyng &amp; ryght Chriſten men, are dryuen to prayer, that they praye ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, truſte and hope one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the helpe and grace
<pb facs="tcp:16259:76"/> of God. Vvhen then ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe is perfourmed, euen then do there ſprynge vp other &amp; good holy workes, that men do thanke God for hys helpe and grace, that men prayſe hys bountifulnes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte other men, lykewyſe in the ſame. All theſe thynges are mere goddes ſeruices, &amp; exceding good workes, which wedlocke miniſtreth dayly vnto our handes, that the fayth and prayer ceaſſe not. But muſt be continually oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyed, whyleſt nowe ioye, nowe ſorrowe, then neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, helpe and delyueraunce appeare, whiche eyther ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue occaſyon to thanke, or el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les to praye.</p>
            <p>Therfore ſayth the text
<pb facs="tcp:16259:76"/> here well and truely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke is a noble honourable &amp; coſtly lyfe, which god hath not onely ordeyned, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with hys bleſſyng, and alſo all ſainctes haue praiſed with theyr lyues and conuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſations, as a gloryous worke of god, leauyng vs an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But wedlocke is alſo to be prayſed for thys cauſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſticketh thoroughout full of good workes, as is nowe reherſed.<note place="margin">Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is full of good workes</note> That a maried ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and a maryed woman, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do nothynge within the hous of ſo ſmall reputacion, belon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynge to the houſſe kepyng, or bringynge vp of children, but that it is a holy worke, &amp; acceptable to God, and that it is done after the word, wil
<pb facs="tcp:16259:77"/> and ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore proſperite &amp; welth muſt nedes be accompanyed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iij</note>Therfore hath Chriſt him ſelfe matrimony in ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that he cometh perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his dearly beloued mother and Apoſtles to the mariage in Cana, in Galile, and there manifeſteth hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe with a glorious miracle by tournyng water into wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. To thintent that he the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re by woulde ſignifye bothe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he loueth the ſtate of matri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mony, &amp; that he wil geue his bleſſynge therein. This bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſynge ſhal alwayes remaine among the maried, as farre as they as the C.xxviij.<note place="margin">Pſalm. Cxxviij</note> Pſalme ſayth, feare God, &amp; walke in his waies. Forwhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reas
<pb facs="tcp:16259:77"/> men wil deſpiſe the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of God, lyue in ſynne wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tingly, and vſe not the loue, which in eſpeciall ought to be betwene man and wyfe. But wyl chyde and brawle, one with another fyght and vſe all maner of frowarde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. There is it no marueyll that in the ſtede of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, foloweth infelicite, and all maner of calamitie. for what goodnes is there to be hoped for, where as no feare of God is, yea where God is refuſed, and thorough many maner of ſynnes the dore is bolted for him &amp; hys bleſſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges?</p>
            <p>Therfore ſayth not the tex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te here ſo ſlightly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wedlock
<pb facs="tcp:16259:78"/> is to be had in honoure and pryce.<note place="margin">Vvhat the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defyled bedde is</note> But he addeth alſo thereunto thys worde, and the bedde vndefyled. Vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby he wil ſet furth in pictu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, howe wedlocke ſhall be kepte, whiche he hath pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo highly. And firſt he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth vtterly the ryght de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fylynge of the bedde in wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, among the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that men beware of horedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me &amp; aduoutry, as he doth call it hereafter. for thys is the groſſeſt and greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fylyng of the bedde, wherby the laudable and honorable ſtate of matrimony is pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the ordinaunce of God diuided. And occaſion is geuen, to all aduerſitye, here bodely, and here after
<pb facs="tcp:16259:78"/> perpetually.</p>
            <p>Moreouer it maye alſo be called defilynge of the bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,<note place="margin">Other defylyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of the bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimony</note> whatſoeuer geueth occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that the hertes betwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne man and wife be withdra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen the one from the other, and are moued to diſſention, hatred and other vnkynde conuerſacion. for out of this foloweth commonly the groſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe defilinge whereof we ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſpoken a littel before. yf nowe man and wyfe wyl ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe their bedde pure &amp; cleane as hath ben ſayd, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt they eſchewe all occaſions, whereby they myght be mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued to frowardenes &amp; to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. Not be wilfull nor arrogant, not interpretate euery thynge for the worſte.
<pb facs="tcp:16259:79"/> But the one muſt beare w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the other, and ſuffer a word, not onely to entretayne fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyppe and amitye, But alſo bycauſe we knowe that it is the wyl and pleaſure of god, and that the worde and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of God requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſame of vs. for as ſoo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne as the hertes are bittered the one agaynſte the other, So hath the Deuyl founde a holl ready, that withoute any labour he can rente ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimony a ſunder agayne, and put it to trouble, in ſo muche that alſo the bodyes are ſeparated.</p>
            <p>Therfore, here muſte be vſed the diſcretion betwene man and wyfe, where of S. Peter ſpeaketh .i.<note place="margin">i. Pet. iij.</note> Petri. iij.
<pb facs="tcp:16259:79"/> That the men ſhoulde dwell with theyr wyues according to knowledge, geuynge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them honour as vnto the weaker veſſell, that theyr prayers be notletted tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough ſtubbernes and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes. for it is the offyce of a man, as of the heade that he ſhall not rule Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannouſly, but diſcretely, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to reaſon, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme wynke and beare with the weakenes whiche ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reygneth in the woman kynde, conſiderynge theyr fraylnes, and not theyr ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyte or wilfulnes.</p>
            <p>Contrarywyſe it ſhal alſo be the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s part,<note place="margin">Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> to know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge ſuche theyr naturall
<pb facs="tcp:16259:80"/> weakenes, and ſuffer theſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me not to moche. But refray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne themſelues with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not thorough much and immoderate repetinge, the huſband be moued to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte anger. An amiable worde and obedyent ſtylnes, maye quenche muche debate, and hatred, whereas elles, out of pratynge and murmuryng agayne, there myght follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we anger and ſtrypes, &amp; beſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des that al miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>Where nowe theſe two poyntes are betwene man &amp; wyfe,<note place="margin">Two princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall poyntes of the maried.</note> that thei be chaſte and circumſpecte, and fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly one to another in worde &amp; dede. There is wedlocke, as the Epiſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ebrewes in thys place doth call it, a noble
<pb facs="tcp:16259:80"/> worthy and honourable con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſation, where in not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly men of vnderſtondynge do delyte, but alſo God hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in heauen, with all hys angels and ſayntes. But whereas there is a faute in eyther of them, that is to ſaye, that eyther through ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoutry and hooredome the bedde of matrimony is defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or elles by the reaſon of vnkynde, and wilde conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacion and dwellynge toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the hertes are moued one agaynſt another, there is it not to be feared, that God wyl come as a iudge, &amp; punyſhe ſuche vngodlynes and inordinate lyuynge. for here is it written, as for who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rekepers and aduouterers,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:81"/> God ſhall iudge them.</p>
            <p>For as muche nowe as the Deuyll ſpecially ſeketh bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wene man and wyfe to moue them, eyther to horedome, or at the leaſt to ſowe diſcorde &amp; variaunce betwene them, we ought not onely to fyght dayly agaynſt this tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with an earneſt prayer vnto God, and to ſeke reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at hys hande. But alſo to kepe &amp; vſe oure ſelues there to w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al diligence, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we our ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues geue none occaſion vnto ſuche crafty worke, &amp; prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of the deuyl. for this is not the ſmaleſt parte of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſyng, where ſuch dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge together in wedlocke, is preſerued in continuall vnitye and amitye.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:81"/>
            <p>And the maried nede not themſelues,<note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryed cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de not make their ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te bitter them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues</note> by vngentel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue oure or wordes to geue occaſyon of malyce or euyll wyll betwene them. for they ſhall fynde euery daye occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon ynough, vnſought and vnloked for, where by they ſhall be moued and prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to indignation, hatred curſynge and other vngra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſnes. So that they ſhall haue alwayes ynough to do, for to reſiſte and let the Deuyll of hys purpoſe, bothe by prayer and alſo by circumſpecte diſcretion.</p>
            <p>Therfore is it a good and godly ordinaunce, that men wyſſhe vnto the newe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed coupple, the bleſſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of God before the hole
<pb facs="tcp:16259:82"/> churche, and make a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſupplication for them, that they may begynne the ſtate of matrimony in the name of God, and that it may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpere with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de pray for the newe maryed couples</note> for to bye this bleſſynge, yf it were to ſelle, men ſhoulde ſpare no money But nowe doth it the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che without money, neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles ſome men be ſo rude, that they woulde rather be without it. But we maye let them alone. for thei that are Chriſtians, wyll ſo moche the bolder geue themſelues into the ſtate of matrimony, euen for thys common pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſake.</p>
            <p>For wedlocke, yf the holy bedde remayne vndefyled, is an honourable &amp; excellent
<pb facs="tcp:16259:82"/> eſtate, for as moche as God hymſelfe hath ordeyned and inſtituted it, and alſo geuen hys bleſſyng therevnto, and in general the Examples of al ſainctes do teache vs this lyfe, where in we haue euery houre aboundauntly, al ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of occaſions to ſerue god and our neyghbour, as we haue heard before.</p>
            <p>Yf nowe any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorough thys honourable predicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will not be moued to the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of matrimony,<note place="margin">The ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hooreke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pers god ſhal iudge them</note> let hym be moued yet by thys, that the texte ſpeaketh wiſh manifeſt wordes, of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that lyue oute of wedlocke, or otherwyſe in vnclenlynes. The aduoute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and hoorekepers ſhall god iudge. for here doeſt thou
<pb facs="tcp:16259:83"/> heare, althoughe there we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re no man in earth that kne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we ſuch vnclenlynes of the, or coulde punyſſhe the ſame, that yet thou ſhalt not eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe. But thou muſt come befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re the iudgement of god, and he ſhall iudge the accordyng as he fyndeth the. And thus ſayth ſaynt Paule,<note place="margin">i. Cor vi</note> i. Cor. vi. Be not deceaued, for neither fornicatours, neither aduou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trers ſhall inherite the kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of heauen.</p>
            <p>Here doth he pretely tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the thoughtes, whiche ſticke in many men, whiche thynke that it is not a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſynne, to lyue oute of wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>locke, and yet to vſe vnclen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, Accordyng as we ſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the world thoroughout cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:16259:83"/> this ſynne but ſmal, but wilt thou knowe, yf men wil not be conuerted, what the ende ſhall be: Then herken to thys. Thou ſhalt not inhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryte the kyngdome of God. Thys ſhal be the iudgement of God, ouer the aduoute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and fornicatours.</p>
            <p>Nowe reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber thou, what thou ſhalt kepe, when thou haſte loſte the kyngedome of God. Therfore let euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ware of thys iudgement of God, and take hede in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, that he may amende his lyfe, and eſchue vncle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lynes. Otherwyſe, although there followed no temporal correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet ſhall not the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God be left oute. for there is dubble ſynne,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:84"/> that men eſchue matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for a tryfle, and defyle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues with ſynne the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger the more contrary to the wil of God. There vpon muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des followe the iudgement of god, for here is none other meane nor cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl, but that thou leaue ſuche vnclenly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and geue thy ſelfe into thys ſtate of wedlocke. And ſo not onely prayſe this ſtate hygh and honourable, with wordes, but alſo with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and kepe the bedde of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimony vndefyled, through chaſtite, and gentell conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation and dwellynge toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Thys be ſayde for a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, and inſtruction, not onely for the yonge peoples
<pb facs="tcp:16259:84"/> ſake, whiche yet ſhal come to the ſtate of mariage. But al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo for their ſakes, that are in wedlock all ready. That thei bothe may knowe, wherfore they ſhall take wedlock, and howe they ſhall behaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues therein Godly. To the intent that God be with them, with hys bleſſynge, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that they maye haue a good conſcience therby, which God graunt vnto vs all.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:85"/>
            <head>☞A briefe Exhortation vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the maryed couple, howe they ſhall behaue themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in wedlocke</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore god dyd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute wedloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E knowe oute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce matrimony hath hys beginnyng, na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mely, that it is an ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god, that the man and wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man ſhoulde dwel together, and ſpende theyr lyues one with another. fyrſte for thys cauſe, that by thys meanes the ſynne and the fleſh ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be letted, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we might lyue in a good conſcience. for god hath ſharply prohibited horedome &amp; vnclenlynes, &amp; puniſhed the ſame greuouſly, as we ſe in all hiſtoryes &amp; by daily experience. Secondely alſo for thys cauſe, that the
<pb facs="tcp:16259:85"/> kyngdome of god, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> church may be entre tained, not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly by thys, that god through hys bleſſyng ſendeth childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in wedlocke, But alſo, that the children are educated of the maryed men, &amp; brought vp in the worde and feare of god, to thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of god, and the ryghte goddes ſeruyce may alway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es come from the one, vpon the other, by inheritaunce, and by the meanes thereof, many maye come to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Wherfore,<note place="margin">God ſo to be thanked for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony</note> ſeynge wedloc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke ſerueth agaynſt ſynne, &amp; for the increaſſynge of the kyngdome of god, So ought ye, and all they that come to the State of matrymonye,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:86"/> to thanke god with al youre hertes, for thys grace, that he hath geuen you ſuch a her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and mynde, that ye haue no luſt to vnclenlynes, and ſynne, as the vngodly worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. But feare god, and deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to eſchue all vnclenlynes: for thys is a great grace, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge thys example is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that Sathan hath ſo many maner of ſnares, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re by he kepeth the hertes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they out of wedlocke conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in ſynne, and in an euyl conſcience. But what iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhal followe them that vſe ſuche vnclenlines, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſaint Paule .i.<note place="margin">i. Cor. vi</note> Corin. vi. Neyther fornicatours, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aduouterers ſhal inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the kyngdome of god,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:86"/> from thys fearful ſentence, are ye (thankes be to God) now eſcaped, yf ye kepe your ſelues together, and dwell together, accordynge to the ordinaunce of God.</p>
            <p>But yet ye ſhal not be with out feare:<note place="margin">the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye lay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth way<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and wyfe.</note> for the wicked ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mye, ſeynge, he coulde not hynder your hertes, &amp; youre Godly purpoſes, He ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dertake and attempte other wayes, to come to you, and to diuide ſuche matrimonial dwellyng together, or at the leaſt, to make it heauy &amp; pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefull. And thys is ſpecially hys pretenſe, to ſtudye howe he may plucke the hertes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye the one from the other that euen as nowe ye haue luſte &amp; loue one to another,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:87"/> he maye rayſe lothſomnes &amp; enemitie.</p>
            <p>And the deuyl fyndeth by vs a great aduauntage, for this hys purpoſe. For there to are we vſed euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oure youth, through ſynne, that eueryone woulde fayne ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ryght, counte hys brayne for the beſte, and be vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge to geue place, or forbea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re the other. But thys ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not for an vnite, but for diſcorde, wherfore the mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed couple muſt beware for it, with all diligence, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly praye vnto God for his holy Goſt, that he wyll ſo gouerne them, and ſo knyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te theyr hartes together, that the wicked enemy may not ſowe hys ſede betwene
<pb facs="tcp:16259:87"/> them, and ſeparate the her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes a ſunder.</p>
            <p>Suche a prayer is hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and very neceſſarye,<note place="margin">They that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in wedloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke muſt praye God that thei maye lyue in vnitie.</note> that it maye go ſo dayly with them, that are in wedlocke, and that alwayes the one praye for the other, that it wyll pleaſe God, to defende them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuche enormyties. But becauſe that there are fewe men, that remembre theſame, and yet fewer that do it, and praye earneſtly, Therfore do we ſe, howe the Deuyll hath his playe, that there are very fewe of ſuch men, amonge whome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred chydynge, curſynge, brawlynge, reuylynge, and fightynge is not vſed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:89"/>
            <p>And they ſe not, that the Deuyll woulde fayne haue it ſo, and that it cometh by hys inſtigation, or elles they woulde not onely praye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt it, but alſo endeuour themſelues to reſiſte the ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyll aſſaultes of the Deuyll, and to geue no rowme to wrath, yf it would ſtirre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to brawlynge or to fyghtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, for it is the ryghte worke of the Deuyll: whiche yf me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll followe, the matter wil waxe worſe and worſe, and one myſchief will brynge in another.</p>
            <p>For thys is true withoute doute, that through ſuch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnynge, the Deuyll bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it to that paſſe, that at the laſt, the hertes ſeparate
<pb facs="tcp:16259:89"/> them ſelues one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that the loue va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſheth awaye quyte. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re muſt nedes followe then a wretched lyfe, where as a couple ſhould be together, &amp; yet ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not endure together, &amp; yet is thys plage vety com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon in the world. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce cometh ſhe? The people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard not the enemye the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and therfore they praye not, that god wyll withſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and reſyſte hym. And thei themſelues knowe not, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they frette, crake and face, and wyl not forbeare one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, that they do but ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue rowme to the Deuyl, for to accomplyſhe hys purpoſe. Now yf thou wylt he defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from ſuche miſchief, and
<pb facs="tcp:16259:90"/> deſyreſt to poſſeſſe a peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, amiable, &amp; agreable wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>locke with thy bedfellowe, Then learne to praye vnto God for it, that it will pleaſe hym, through the holy Goſt to rule your hartes, to with ſtande Sathan, and to kepe you in vnitie and concorde. Next vnto thys prayer, muſt alſo be vſed a ſynguler dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, Wherof Saynt Peter te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acheth i.<note place="margin">i. Pet. iij</note> Pet. iij. Ye menne, ſayth he, dwell with your wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues accordynge to knowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, geuing honour vnto the wife, as vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weaker veſſel &amp; as vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are heyres al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo of the grace of lyfe,<note place="margin">Vvhat the man ought to do.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your prayers be not let. This com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t goeth ſpecially v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the man, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhal begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:90"/> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e to it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnitie &amp; loue maye be entretayned in wedlocke &amp; thys is brought to paſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n this wyſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le with diſcretion, and not with extremitie take the wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the worſte in euerye thynge. A good cauſe why? For the woman is a weake creature, and hath not ſuche a courage nor ſtronge herte as a man: They are ſone tempted, and pricked at the herte, and are ſooner moued to myrth and ſorrowe, then the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. This ought a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to conſyder, and be not hard agaynſt them, but ſomtyme he muſt diſſemble ſomewhat and wynke at a faute, &amp; help it with a fayre worde,</p>
            <p>But thys diſcretion taketh
<pb facs="tcp:16259:91"/> the worlde for a wyuyſh thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, and thincketh that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth well, a man to be angry, and to fyghte wel S. Peter ſeeth well ynough,<note place="margin">Howe men ſhoulde geue ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> what becommeth the man beſt, and wherein he oughte to be mooſt diligent. He bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not to ſtryke. Vſe diſcre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion ſayth he. And that whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is more, he biddeth the to geue her, her honour, that is, to fauour &amp; forbeare her for thys cauſe, that ſhe is a weake veſſel, ſhe hath a faint weake and fearfull herte, &amp; is brought alofte and moued to wrath with one worde. Le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>arne thys and forbeare, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewith ſhalt thou not onely kepe vnitie, But alſo ouerco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me the herte. For with fayre
<pb facs="tcp:16259:91"/> wordes is alwayes more got<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten amonge reaſonable tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, then with ſtrypes.</p>
            <p>But he that wyl nothyng forbeare a woman, but wyll be alwayes curſyng and figh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinge, and doynge ſuche ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke thynges, what good doth the ſame? He helpeth the De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyll to accomplyſhe his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, that where as vnitie, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue and ioye ought to be, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there groweth enemitie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and enuye. Thys is in it ſelfe a heauy caſe, and dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teles the greateſt inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, that can come to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hande in worldely mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>But there is yet another let,<note place="margin">Diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and malice hynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth prayer.</note> whereby prayer is letted or hyndered. For whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:16259:92"/> is diſcorde, there can be no ryght prayer made. For the Pater noſter, or prayer goeth not for vs alone, but for the hole worlde. And ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially we comprehende there in, that we wil forgeue them that treſpaſſe agaynſte vs, as we woulde that god ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de forgeue vs. Howe can ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che contentious perſons do? Howe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they pray for other, where the one is ſo bittered agaynſt the other? And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prayer for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and other is loſt, what conforte and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence wyll they haue then? Seynge, we can none other wyſe, but by prayer eſcape from the Deuyll. And alſo haue no conforte and helpe in all maner of neceſſities,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:92"/> whereon we maye take hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de.</p>
            <p>Lo, into ſuche temporal &amp; ſpirituall calamities doeſt thou brynge thy ſelfe, when thou wylt be vndiſcrete, and vſe no diſcretion. But euen as madde horſes, ſtryke and byte aboute the. Saynt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth not bidde it the: But the Deuyll doth loue it: ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore beware of it: Thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt be a man well ynough, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou ſtryke not ſo aboute the, and ſuffereſt of thy bedfellowe a worde or two. Thys ought the man to do, and it is acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to God, and it bringeth to man and wyfe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues al goodnes, and al maner of bleſſynges into their hous.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:93"/>
            <p>But what ſhal the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do? Shall ſhe abuſe ſuch for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearyng and diſcrete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and do alwaies what ſhe luſteth? No, thys were al ſo contrary to the commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement of God. For ſaint Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter alſo preacheth vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on thys wyſe.<note place="margin">i. Pe. iij. Howe the wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues ought to vſe them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues</note> Let the wiues be inſubiection to theyr huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. To be in ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is not, to rule &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. This ought a woman to do ouer her familye and children. But to her huſband ſhe muſt be in ſubiection, ſuffer to be commaunded, and followe. Thys is alſo a great poynt, whiche to concorde helpeth very much, whan a woman loketh on her huſbande, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoureth herſelfe to kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we
<pb facs="tcp:16259:93"/> and accompliſhe his wil, and doeth that thing, which ſhe knoweth to be hys plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And eſchueth that thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, which ſhe knoweth, that he loueth not. For by thys doth ſhe wynne her huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des herte, that he hath luſte and ioye to come home agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to hys wyfe. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe whan the wyues be diſobe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyent, ſelf mynded, frowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, the man abhorreth hys owne hous, thynkynge, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he cometh into the houſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he muſt go to the battail and amonge hys enemyes.</p>
            <p>But nowe it is not well poſſible, but that ſomtyme ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che thynges muſt nedes be ſene. For we are al frayl and vnparfect, ſpecially the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb facs="tcp:16259:94"/> more then the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the woman muſt bewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, that ſhe continue not in obſtinacie and diſobedience. But knowledge her treſpace and ſaye, Good huſbande, this and that worde eſcaped me in myne anger. I praye you, forgeue it me, I wyll do it no more. Thys ought the women to do in eſpecial, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are mooſt fauty.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues muſt be to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to theyr huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note>And to thys doynge ſhall not onely the commodity dry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue them, that by the reaſon thereof they myght lyue in quiete and vnite: But alſo the ſtrayghte commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God: Wherof ſaynt Paule ſpeaketh.<note place="margin">Ephe. v</note> Epheſi. v where he ſayth. Vvemen ſubmitte your ſelues vnto
<pb facs="tcp:16259:94"/> your owne huſbandes as vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the Lorde. For the huſban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de is the wyues heade, euen as Chriſte is the head of the congregation. Therfore as the congregation is in ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Chriſte, Lykewyſe let the wyues be in ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to theyr huſbandes in all thinges.</p>
            <p>Item let the wyfe ſe,<note place="margin">Ephe. v</note> that ſhe feare her huſbande. There ſeeſt thou, that it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo the ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god, that thou ſhalt knowledge thy huſbande, as thy Lorde and Mayſter, and honoure hym with feare and obedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.<note place="margin">i. Pet. iii</note> And ſaynt Peter ſayth in the place aboue mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. That in the olde tyme the holy wemen dyd tyer
<pb facs="tcp:16259:95"/> themſelues, not with ſyluer and golde, but that they tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſted in God, and were obedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to their huſbandes, euen as Sara obeyed Abraham,<note place="margin">Gene. xviij.</note> and called hym lorde, whoſe doughters ye are, ſayth Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yf ye followe theyr exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The paynes and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayl of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note>Thys ſayeng ſhoulde the wyues marke in eſpecial. It is very true, that the mooſt paine in wedlock goeth ouer the wyues, they loſe theyr li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berte, and muſt ſuffer greate calamity and miſerye in wed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>locke, with bearyng of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and with nouryſſhyng and bryngyng them vp, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reof they ſhoulde be fre, yf they were not in wedlocke. Notwithſtandyng here ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:16259:95"/> Saynt Peter: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this was the tyeringe of the holy wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that they dyd put their truſt in God: that is: They dyd not abhorre wedlocke for ſuche diſquietnes and ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſities ſakes. They gaue themſelues gladly into it, &amp; truſted in God: that is: they had to God thys confidence, that he ſhoulde helpe them, and therfore they called vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for help. This do thou likewyſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> arte thou good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly garnyſhed and tyered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, all hys Angelles &amp; Saynctes.<note place="margin">The at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the fayreſt women.</note> And nedeſt not from thencefurth to loke for good workes. Be obedyente vnto thy huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, take, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of hym, haue reſpecte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym, and loke what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyreth
<pb facs="tcp:16259:96"/> and wyl haue of the. Herewith doeſt thou ſerue God, and entrtaineſt peace and vnitie in thy houſe.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, it ſhall alſo come to paſſe, that god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his grace and bleſſynge will be with the and thy wyfe, and wil cauſe al goodnes to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto you, as the C.xxviij. Pſalme ſayth.<note place="margin">Pſalm. C.xxviij</note> Bleſſed is he, that feareth the Lorde, and walketh in his waies. Thou ſhalt enioye the labours of thyne owne handes O well is the, happie arte thou: thy wyfe ſhall be, as a frutefull vynearde rounde about thy houſſe. Thy children lyke the olyue braunches rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute thy table. Lo, thus ſhal the man be bleſſed, that
<pb facs="tcp:16259:96"/> feareth the Lorde:</p>
            <p>Therfore learne now, thus to guyde yourſelues in wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, then are ye alwayes prouyded. From the Deuils ſnare, as from the vnclenly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes oute of wedlocke are ye eſcaped, in ſo moche that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God ye may haue a good conſcience: for he hymſelfe hath ordeyned thys ſtate of matrimony. And ſeynge ye pray dayly vnto God, that it wyll pleaſe him to aſſiſte you dayly with hys grace, and kepe you in loue and vnitie. And alſo vſe youre ſelues to thys, with a ſpecial diligence that ye be ſtyl and peaceable and take well in worth the dayly tranſgreſſions &amp; faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes one of another. Therfore
<pb facs="tcp:16259:97"/> ſhall your dwellynge be fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely and louing, that ye ſhal haue luſt and ioye thereon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Man and wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe maye praye in aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye.</note>And although the Croſſe, which vndoubtedly ſhal not abyde oute, do ouertake you that nowe here, nowe there happeneth ſome miſfortune, and that it proſpereth not well, then maye ye yet lyfte vp your handes together in ſuche a common neceſſitie, &amp; crye to God, for helpe. And the promyſe is euen there at hande, which Chriſt pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth Matth. in the xviij.<note place="margin">Mathe xviij.</note> of two of you ſhall agree in earth vpon any maner of thynge, whatſoeuer they ſhall deſyre, it ſhall be geuen them of my father which is in heauen. Wherfore woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb facs="tcp:16259:97"/> thou then abhorre neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſite, ſeyng helpe is promyſed vnto the, and it fayleth in nothynge, but that thou &amp; thy wyfe as a ryghte and ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le churche of God praye for it? Alſo thou knoweſt thys, that it behoueth vs Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to beare the Croſſe.</p>
            <p>Therfore thanke God for thys grace, as I haue tolde you at the beginnyng, that ye are come to the holy ſtate of matrimony: And praye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god wyll rule and gouerne you therein, &amp; preſerue you from ſynne and all inconue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niences. And ſpecially do your diligence, that ye ſuffer not Sathan to crepe in, through anger, and obſtina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie: That your prayer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyeſt
<pb facs="tcp:16259:98" rendition="simple:additions"/> confort, be not let, and that ye may crye to god for helpe in all neceſſities, and kepe hys bleſſynge, grace, protecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on and defence, vntyll god brynge you with youres to another and better lyfe. Vvhere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to helpe vs the grace in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16259:98"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
